<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Politikos megas the grand politician, or, The secret art of state-policy discovered in evident demonstrations of unparalleled prudence, and confirmed with wonderful and successful adventures, stratagems and exploits of wisdom and subtility, both in peace and war, by the most remarkable witts of former ages : being a treatise both useful and necessary for all nobles, states-men, judges, lawyers justices of peace, officers of wars, and all such as now are, or may happen to stand at the helm of publick affairs, whether in kingdom or commonwealth / written originally in Latin by Conradus Reinking, Chancellour ot His Electoral Highness the Duke of Brandenburg, and now done into English by a careful hand.</title>
            <author>Reinking, Conradus.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1691</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 200 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 86 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A47277</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing K342A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R32439</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12696542</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12696542</idno>
            <idno type="VID">65868</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A47277)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 65868)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1529:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Politikos megas the grand politician, or, The secret art of state-policy discovered in evident demonstrations of unparalleled prudence, and confirmed with wonderful and successful adventures, stratagems and exploits of wisdom and subtility, both in peace and war, by the most remarkable witts of former ages : being a treatise both useful and necessary for all nobles, states-men, judges, lawyers justices of peace, officers of wars, and all such as now are, or may happen to stand at the helm of publick affairs, whether in kingdom or commonwealth / written originally in Latin by Conradus Reinking, Chancellour ot His Electoral Highness the Duke of Brandenburg, and now done into English by a careful hand.</title>
                  <author>Reinking, Conradus.</author>
                  <author>Ker, Patrick, fl. 1691.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[17], 150 p. : port.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Tho. Howkins ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCXCI [1691]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication and translator's preface signed Pat. Ker.</note>
                  <note>Contains engraved portrait frontispiece.</note>
                  <note>"Licensed and entred according to order."</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: pages faded and torn with print show through and loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Political science --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Political ethics.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:65868:1"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>Vera Effigies Conradi Reinking Anno Aetatis Suoe. <hi>43.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <figDesc>portrait of Conradus Reinking</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Printed for Thomas Howkins, in George Yard In Lombard ſtreet.</hi>
            </p>
            <byline>F. H. van. Hove. Sculp.</byline>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:65868:1"/>
            <p>ΠΟΛΙΤΙΚΟ'Σ ΜΕ'ΓΑΣ: THE <hi>Grand Politician,</hi> OR THE SECRET ART OF State-Policy DISCOVERED.</p>
            <p>IN Evident Demonſtrations of unparelleled Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and confirmed with Wonderful and Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsful Adventures, Stratagems, and Exploits of Wiſdom and Subtilty; both in Peace and War, by the moſt remarkable Witts of former Ages.</p>
            <p>BEING A <hi>Treatiſe</hi> both uſeful and neceſſary for all Nobles, States-Men, Judges, Lawyers, Juſtices of Peace, Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of War, and all ſuch as now are, or may happen to ſtand at the Helm of Publick Affairs, whether in Kingdom or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Wealth.</p>
            <p>Written Originally in Latin, by <hi>Conradus Reinking</hi> Chancellour to his Electoral Highneſs, the Duke of <hi>Branden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg,</hi> and now done into Engliſh, by a careful Hand.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Golz.</hi>
               </bibl> Prudentia gubernantur Regiones, quarum limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes tyrannide nunquam extenduntur.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>Licenſed and Entred according to Order.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho. Howkins</hi> in <hi>George Yard in Lombard ſtreet,</hi> MDCXCI,</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:65868:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:65868:2"/>
            <head>TO THE Right Honourable, THE <hi>E. of Nottingham,</hi> Principal Secretary of State, TO Their Preſent Majeſties</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>AS there are no Sea-Officers, to whom Gratitude is more due, than Knowing and Careful Pilots; ſo is there no Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, either in Kingdom or Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth,
<pb facs="tcp:65868:3"/>to whom the People owe grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Obligations. Duty, and Reſpect, than to a Wiſe, and Well-deſerving <hi>Secretary of State;</hi> as being one who conſtantly ſtandeth at the Helm of Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Affairs, to Weather the Common Intereſt, againſt all the Storms, and Tempeſts, of Seditious, Vain-glorious, and Aſpiring Oppoſers. For this Cauſe, I have thrown in the Mite of my Humble Reſpects, in the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury of your publick Deſervings, as a Token, and Acknowledgment, of the vaſt Sum of Service and Reſpects, the Kingdom is indebted to your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip's Prudence, Care, and Candor; that if, like the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nthankful Lepers, moſt ſhould prove forgetful of your Lordſhip's Favours, ſome, at leaſt,
<pb facs="tcp:65868:3"/>may Acknowledg the Debt, tho' all be not able to pay the Intereſt. I Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly preſent your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> with this ſmall Treatiſe; Written Originally in Latine, and am ſorry it is of no grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Extract than a Tranſlation: How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, <hi>Non defero Noctuam Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas,</hi> nor profer it as a Supplement to the full Orb of your Lordſhip's Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifications; for the Sun never borrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a Ray from any Inferiour Planet, tho, on Rational Grounds, this ſmall Treatiſe, or little wandring Meteor, beggeth a Beam of your Lordſhip's Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, that, with Confidence, it may appear in the open World. Thus, may it be ſaid, in this Caſe, as <hi>Ovid,</hi> in ſuch another.</p>
            <q>At<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> 
               <hi>Ajax</hi> Armis, non <hi>Ajaci</hi> Arma petuntur.</q>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:65868:4"/>So this ſmall Treatiſe, and Foreign Politician, humbly beggeth the Honour of your Lordſhip's Patronage and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection: which, if granted, will effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually Legittimate all the Miſtakes, and Overſights, which might have been committed by a <hi>German States-Man.</hi> Thus, humbly begging your Lordſhip's Acceptance, I make bold to Subſcribe my Self,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhip's moſt Humble, and Devoted Servant, <hi>PAT. KER.</hi>
               </signed>
               <date>Auguſt <hi>27. 1690.</hi>
               </date>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:65868:4"/>
            <head>THE TRANSLATOR TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Here preſent you with, this little Treatiſe of <hi>German Policy:</hi> And tho perhaps you may repute your ſelf as Wiſe as the Author, you may reap here ſome Ears of Wiſdom, Prudence, and Policy, as may reliſh the Appetite of your Expectation, and keep you from grudging the peruſal of ſo ſmall a Book. It is come of a <hi>German</hi> Pedigree, written Originally in Latine (tho never hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in Print) by the famous and well known Miniſter of State, <hi>Conradus Rein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king,</hi> Chancellour to his <hi>Electoral High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> the <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Brandenburgh,</hi> and at the Requeſt of ſome his Country Men, here at <hi>London,</hi> now Tranſlated into <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and publiſhed to the Worlds
<pb facs="tcp:65868:5"/>view. I wiſh the Book may be reputed as famous within the Iſle of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> as the Author was in his own Country. And it is reaſon that we ſhould be kind to this Stranger, which preſenteth to us the firſt Fruits of a <hi>German Wit,</hi> before it's own Country-men. The Subject is great, and much to be deſired; for as <hi>Phocilides</hi> ſaith,
<q>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</l>
                  <l>Agros, Navem, urbes ſapientia ſola gubernat.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Et</hi> Pythagoras.
<q>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</l>
                  <l>Et vis, et telum, et Murus, prudentia vitae eſt.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>And as it is great and much deſireable, ſo is it but by few attainable, tho every one, for the moſt part, reputeth himſelf a Politician, and able to manage Affairs of greateſt weight and conſequence. Thus <hi>Reader,</hi> leaving the Cenſure of this <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Politician,</hi> to your own gentle Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and courteous candour, I reſt</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Friend and Servant, <hi>P. K.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:65868:5"/>
            <head>THE Contents.</head>
            <list>
               <item>THE Art of perſuading to a Belief of Things unknown. <hi>Intrigue 1. Page 3.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Art of perſuading one that you know another's Secrets. <hi>Int. 2 p. 5</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Art of obtaining what you deſire from your Enemy. <hi>Int. 3 p. 6</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Art of obtaining what one deſireth, without asking, but by giving occaſion. <hi>Int. 4 p. 8</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Art of obtaining hard and difficult Things, <hi>Intr. 5 p. 9</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How to diſarm and weaken an Enemy. <hi>Int. 6 p. 12</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How to Diſſemble. <hi>Int. 7 p. 15</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How to perſuade, and diſſuade, <hi>Int. 8 p. 17</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How to obtain what you deſire, without danger of loſing the Favour of him whom you deſire it of. <hi>Int. 9 p. 30</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How to obtain what you deſire, when the Perſon whom you deſire it of is altogether averſe. <hi>Int. 10 p. 3</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:65868:6"/>How to force a Confeſſion from one who is obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate. <hi>Int. 11 p. 33</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How to force a thing from one by that which he moſt hateth. <hi>Int. 12 p. 34</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How to ſearch out another's Secrets. <hi>Int. 13 p. 40</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How to find out ones Secrets, by Inſinuating with another who is privy to them. <hi>Int. 14 p. 41</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How to induce one to confeſs all his ſecret faults. <hi>Int. 15 p. 44</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How to find out the Secrets of Drunken Men. <hi>Int. 16 p. 45</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How to find out the Secrets of Sober Men. <hi>Int. 17 p. 46</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How one may know what Reputation he is of, and what is his Character in the Eyes of others. <hi>Int. 18 p. 47</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How one may find out the Judgment of others, in a Caſe that concerneth himſelf. <hi>Int. 19 p. 48</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How to know whether a ſuſpected Perſon be Guilty or not. <hi>Int. 20 p. 51</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How to know Secrets from Nature and Cuſtom. <hi>Int. 21 p. 53</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How to prevent and eſcape ſuddain Snares. <hi>Int. 22 p. 54</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How to anſwer difficult and dubious Queſtions, without danger. <hi>Int. 23 p. 55</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How to ſhun an Offenſive Anſwer or Sentence. <hi>Int. 24 p. 57</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How to ſhun a difficult Sentence. <hi>Int. 25 p. 58</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:65868:6"/>How to ſpeak ones Mind freely without danger. <hi>Int. 26 p. 62</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How to ſpeak what one pleaſeth, without any dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. <hi>Int. 27 p. 63</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How to ſhun the Reproach of an unhappy Adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. <hi>Int. 28 p. 64</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How to ſpeak that which in it ſelf, is dangerous without hurt. <hi>Int. 29 p. 66</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How to ſhun that which is hateful to one, by a Jeſt. <hi>Int. 30 p. 67</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How to reveal a Secret, without giving Offence to him who did inform you of it. <hi>Int. 31 p. 68</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How to reprove one without giving Offence. <hi>Int. 32 p. 69</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How to ſhun the Inconveniences of Jeers and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs. <hi>Int. 33 p. 70</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How to induce a Prince to hear one patiently. <hi>Int. 34 p. 73</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How one ought to behave himſelf, and what courſe he ſhould take when he is environ'd with danger and difficulties on all ſides. <hi>Int. 35 p. 74</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How Princes may conceal their hatred and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate diſpleaſure. <hi>Int. 36 p. 75</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How to aſſuage the Inſolencies of a ſeditions City. <hi>Int. 37 p. 76</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How to abrogate Priviledges. <hi>Int. 38. ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How a Prince may fruſtrate an Enemy, with whom he intendeth to wage War. <hi>Int. 39 p. 77</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:65868:7"/>How a weak Kingdom or Common-wealth may be delivered from the power of a potent Enemy. <hi>Int. 40 p. 78</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How to moleſt Neighbouring Nations. <hi>Int. 41 p. 80</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How to ſuppreſs thoſe who are proud of their honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Titles and Dignities. <hi>Int. 42 p. 81</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How to keep under Men of ambitious and aſpiring Spirits. <hi>Int. 43 p. 82</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How to ſuppreſs ſeditious Souldiers. <hi>Int. 44 p. 84</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How to ſuppreſs civil Seditions and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>proars. <hi>Int. 45 p. 85</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How to know whether an Informer ſpeaketh Truth or not. <hi>Int. 46 p. 87</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How one ought to behave himſelf when he receiveth an injury from a perſon of Quality, far a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove him. <hi>Int. 47 p. 88</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How to ſhun the Envy of Courtiers. <hi>Int. 48 p. 89</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How one ought to behave himſelf with offended Princes and Peers. <hi>Int. 49 p. 91</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How to ſuppreſs the Vices and wrong Sentences of partial Judges. <hi>Int. 50 p. 92</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How to ſuppreſs Luxury. <hi>Int. 51 p. 93</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How to render populous Cities unfit for Seditions and Inſurrections, without loſs or detriment. <hi>Int. 52 p. 94</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How to appeaſe an incenſed People. <hi>Int. 53 p. 95</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How to keep the Favour of New Subjects. <hi>Int. 54 p. 96</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Why Merchandizing is forbidden to the Nobility. <hi>Int. 55 p. 98</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:65868:7"/>Concerning the Inſtruments of Power. <hi>Int. 56 p. 99</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How Stateſmen ought to behave themſelves, in aſſuming the Honour of Memorable Acts. <hi>Int. 57 p. 100</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How to appeaſe offended Princes. <hi>Int. 58 p. 101</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How to impoſe Taxes without the offence of the Subjects. <hi>Int. 59 p. 102</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How to Collect Taxes without offending the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects. <hi>Int. 60 p. 103</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How Seditions are raiſed. <hi>Int. 61 p. 104</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How Rebels and Conſpirators are kept cloſe toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in one Body. <hi>Int. 62 p. 106</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Arts and Tricks of Tyrants. <hi>Int. 63 p. 107</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How to puniſh Seditions Peers. <hi>Int. 64 p. 108</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How to prevent Scarcity of Corn. <hi>Int. 65 p. 109</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How to behave in time of Dearth. <hi>Int. 66. p. 110</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How to preſerve Corn. <hi>Int. 67 p. 113</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How a Prince may beſt confer Honours and Places. <hi>Int. 68 p. 114</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How to keep what is conquered by Force of Arms. <hi>Int. 69 p. 115</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How to March an Army through a Foreign Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey. <hi>Int. 70 p. 116</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How a Prince ſhould behave himſelf with a Conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Neighbour, more powerful than himſelf. <hi>Int. 71 p. 117</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How weaker Perſons may prolong time in difficult Matters. <hi>Int. 72 p. 118</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How to deny a thing without offence. <hi>Int. 73. p. 11</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:65868:8"/>How to compoſe Seditions by Interceſſors, <hi>Int. 74 p. 121</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How to Suppreſs Sedition by Force. <hi>Int. 75 p. 122</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How to Suppreſs Sedition by Force of Arms. <hi>Int. 76 p. 123</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How to enter in Covenant. <hi>Int. 77. p. 125</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How to keep up Favour and Authority at Court. <hi>Int. 78. p. 126</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How a Prince, that is at Peace, ſhould behave when his Neighbours are in War. <hi>Int. 79 p. 127</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How to Disband Souldiers. <hi>Int. 80 p. 128</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How Miniſters of State may avoid great Dangers. <hi>Int. 84 p. 129</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How to Aſpire to Promotion. <hi>Int. 85 p. 130</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How to delay an Inevitable War. <hi>Int. 86 p. 131</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How to Govern New Provinces. <hi>Int. 87 p. 132</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How to eſtabliſh and ſettle New Conqueſts. <hi>Int. 88 p. 134</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How to compoſe the Differences of the Nobility. <hi>Int. 89 p. 136</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How one muſt behave that feareth a Repulſe. <hi>Int. 90 p. 136</hi>
               </item>
               <item>What Policy muſt be uſed by a General. <hi>Int. 91 p. 137</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How to cruſh Reproachful Speeches. <hi>Int. 92. p. 138</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How to obtain leave to depart from Court. <hi>Int. 93 Ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How to avoid Envy. <hi>Int. 94 p. 140</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How to ſhare Dominions among Brothers. <hi>Int. 95 p. 141</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:65868:8"/>How to obſerve the due time of making a Truce. <hi>Int. 96 p. 143</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How to change Commanders of an Army <hi>Int. 97 p. 144</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How to draw up an Army. <hi>Int. 98 p. 145</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How Ambaſſadors and Mediators may procure Peace. <hi>Int. 99 p. Ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How to diſſemble the deſire of Peace. <hi>Int. 100 p. 147</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Cauſes of Animoſities and Inſurrections. <hi>Int. 101 p. 148</hi>
               </item>
               <item>What Cautions are to be uſed in propoſing difficult Matters. <hi>Int. 102 p. 149</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:65868:9"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:65868:9"/>
            <head>THE <hi>Grand Politician:</hi> OR, THE SECRET ART OF State-Policy DISCOVERED.</head>
            <div type="proem">
               <head>PROEME.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>POLICY,</hi> in Word or Deed, whether in perſwading Things Incredible, obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Things Deſirable, forcing a belief of Things Impoſſible, of diving into Secrets, of ſhunning Inconveniences, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is as uſeful means, for Prudent and Pious Men, for obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:65868:10"/>a good and lawful end; as dangerous and abuſeful to the Impious and Crafty, to proſecute a Miſchievous Deſign: And, altho <hi>State-Sophiſters</hi> pervert it, to accompliſh their pernicious Projects; the abuſe thereof ought not to take away the right uſe of a Science, ſo Noble and Neceſſary in all Kingdoms and Common-wealths. As alſo, we daily ſee that that Prudence which is attained with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Learning, by mere Experience, in Civil Affairs, is better and ſurer than that of thoſe, who, from the Wit of <hi>Plato,</hi> and others, pretend to build Cities for the Benefit of a <hi>Common-wealth;</hi> in which it is queſtionable, whether Arrogance or Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance hath the upper hand.</p>
               <p>What I here Write, I have had Tryal of, and proved by Experienee, and long Continuance of Time; that thou, who readeſt them, mayſt, ſooner and after a happier and eaſter way, be made capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of ſtanding at the Helm of Pubiick Affairs, and mayſt contribute to thy own, as well as the common Intereſt. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe then, and intend theſe <hi>Max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ims,</hi> and <hi>Stratagems</hi> of Policy to a good and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt end; if thou wouldſt do thy Country Service, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ain thy ſelf Credit, and dye in Favour with thy Prince and People.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:65868:10"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE 1.</hi> The Art of perſwading things unknown.</head>
               <p>THAT your Hearer may believe that which he knoweth not, you muſt, from the Belief of things known, gain ground up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his Belief: Firſt, by telling him things that he knoweth, as if you thought him Ignorant thereof, and that without any Confirmation. Then afterwards you muſt tell him Things which he doth not know, which you deſign he ſhould believe; affirming them ſo confident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as if you had been a Witneſs thereto; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding from the aforeſaid Things known, to perſwade him unknown: After this Method.</p>
               <p>Firſt of all (without committing <hi>Hyperbolys</hi>) faithfully tell him the cleareſt and likelieſt Things, and what ſtand to Reaſon, which he cannot ſuſpect or queſtion; but very demure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and ſhamefaſtly, with a ſmall Stopping or Heſitation; leſt he repute you a precipitant Blab, that ſpeaketh whatever falleth in your Head. But if you ſuſpect that he thinketh that you underſtand not theſe things ſo well as he, avouch them with Confidence, leſt you ſhould be thought to diſſemble. But if you
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:65868:11"/>perceive that he thinketh that you underſtand them as well as himſelf, then (as I have ſaid) offer them with a kind of Heſitation, by tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling him that you are not come to a full cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of them, and that you have them but by report, and <hi>hear-ſay,</hi> which one ought not, eaſily, without queſtioning to believe.</p>
               <p>Then at laſt, to perſwade him to believe that which he knoweth not, tell him, what you ſay, with as much Confidence, as if you had ſeen it. For by telling him at firſt injenuouſly theſe things whereof he is perſwaded (after you have declared that you are not a Babler, nor Credulous, nor Diſſembler; but very cautious, and one that regards the true meaning of what is told you, little minding common Reports) you ſhall likewiſe lead him to the Belief of thoſe Things which he knoweth not.</p>
               <p>Thus <hi>T. Labienus,</hi> after his defeat at the Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of <hi>Pharſalia,</hi> making his eſcape to <hi>Pyrra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chium,</hi> with <hi>Pompey</hi>'s Forces, told Truth and Lyes in a breath;<note place="margin">Frontin. Lib. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> and without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealing the event of the Battle, (in which he told down-right of <hi>Pompey</hi>'s defeat) but, under-hand, told how Fortune was equal on both ſides; foraſmuch, as <hi>Caeſar</hi> was moſt grieviouſly wounded; with as great Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence as if he had ſeen the Wounds Bleeding. By which Story, he did put new Life and Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage in his defeated Souldiers. Truly if <hi>Labi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enus</hi>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:65868:11"/>(who commanded in chief) had ſpoke with any ſort of doubt, or ſtriven to ſmuther the event of the Battle (which was ſo well known to them all) he had not been credited, as to the reſt of his Story, concerning <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s Wounds.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE II.</hi> The Art of perſwading that you know an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other's Secrets.</head>
               <p>YOU ſhall perſwade others that you have come to the knowledge of Secrets, by one who pretends to have the Art of finding out Myſteries, and underſtanding Secret Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, if in their preſence, you give him ſome reward or gratuity, for the diſcovery thereof; for none will ſuſpect that one ſhould beſtow his Gifts for nothing.</p>
               <p>Thus as <hi>Dionyſius</hi> was very Anxious and Thoughtful, how he might eſcape all Snares; there came a Stranger to <hi>Syracuſe,</hi> bragging,<note place="margin">Potienus <hi>5</hi> Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarch. Apoph.</note> how he alone could tell the way how all Plotters might be known before-hand. As he was called to the Caſtle to <hi>Dionyſius,</hi> and every Body elſe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawn. <hi>This</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is the way to render
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:65868:12"/>you ſecure from Plots and Snares; make as if you had Learned of me the</hi> Art <hi>of knowing</hi> Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rators, <hi>before-hand; which you ſhall render more credible, if in the preſence of your Life-Gards, you beſtow on me a</hi> Talent, <hi>as the reward of my Teaching. Dionyſius</hi> being well ſatisfied with the Fancy, gave him a <hi>Talent</hi> accordingly; tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling his Gards how he was taught an admirable <hi>Art</hi> of knowing <hi>Conſpirators;</hi> before-hand: And they, believing it to be ſo, never durſt afterwards be ſo bold as to hear of any Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy againſt him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE. III.</hi> The Art of obtaining what you deſire from your Enemy.</head>
               <p>YOU ſhall obtain what you deſire of your Enemy, if you counterfeit that you fear he ſhall do theſe things which you mainly wiſh he would do. Likewiſe, if you counterfeit that you wiſh thoſe things were done, which you would not at all have to be done.</p>
               <p>Thus <hi>Ventilius,</hi> in the <hi>Parthian</hi> War againſt King <hi>Pacorus,</hi> knowing that a certain Slave (a <hi>Tyrian</hi> by Nation,<note place="margin">Frontin. Lib. <hi>I.</hi> Cap. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> and one of theſe who ſeemed to be of their Allies)
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:65868:12"/>did acqu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>int, the <hi>Parthians</hi> with all things that were done among them, did manage the Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Villain's Treachery ſo, as to ſerve his own Conveniences; for being grieviouſly afraid that the <hi>Parthians</hi> would, without delay, paſs over the <hi>Euphrates,</hi> before the Legions which were in <hi>Cappadocia,</hi> beyond <hi>Mount Taurus,</hi> could join him; he ſo behaved himſelf, that the Traitor perſwaded them, with his wonted Treachery, to a long and troubleſome March, before they paſſed the River: <hi>For,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>if the</hi> Parthians <hi>come over the Mountains, I ſhall eſcape all dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of the Archers, by the Advantage of the Hills. But if they meet me on Champaign Ground (my Forces being ſo few, and theirs ſo many) I ſhall be certainly beat.</hi> The barbarous People being thus ſeduced, by his telling them ſo, they marched their Army along the Valleys, and then finding the Banks of the River become wide, muſt of Neceſſity be at more trouble to make Bridges over them, and to get Tools and Materials for their Buſineſs. Thus they ſpent above Fourty Days to no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, which ſpace of time, <hi>Ventilius</hi> made uſe of, to gather his Forces together; and then ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving got them in a Body, three Days before the <hi>Parthians</hi> could come, marched, met them, gave them Battle, and gain'd the Victory.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="part">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:65868:13"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE IV.</hi> The Art of obtaining what you deſire without asking, but by giving occaſion that it may be profer'd.</head>
               <p>IF you would obtain, without asking what you deſire of another; you muſt firſt inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuate your ſelf in his Favour, by ſome familiar Diſcourſe, relating to your purpoſe; which concerneth both you and him; and then pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe what you intend to obtain, as a thing which (if it were granted) would tend much to his Intereſt. And if this Occaſion be Acceptable, and Take, you may ask down-right. But if not, you muſt ſmooth your Deſign, and ſmuther it, with all the Policy you can. But muſt give ſome other plauſible Reaſon, why of Neceſſity it ought to be done; for which, Reaſons ſake, he may of his own Accord proffer what you deſire.</p>
               <p>Thus upon an honeſt account, <hi>Sertorius</hi> uſed to take and keep <hi>Hoſtages,</hi> ſo as not to be
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:65868:13"/>minded by thoſe who gave them. For they who give willingly do hardly mind that they give. For indeed <hi>Sertorius</hi> (to keep the <hi>Spaniards</hi> Loyal, and that he might, the more ſecurely, live among them) keept a School in <hi>Orca,</hi> a very Large City where he liv'd, and whether the Spaniſh Grandees ſent their Children for education: ſo that in effect he both received and kept Hoſtages, and yet did inſtruct them withall. Thus it may be oft times Lawful to obtain and poſſeſs, under a more ſpecious title, what of it ſelf may look more hateful and contemptible.</p>
               <p>The truth is, if <hi>Sertorius</hi> had uſed the Name of <hi>Hoſtages,</hi> and required them, he ſhould never have had one.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE. V.</hi> The Art of obtaining hard and Difficult things.</head>
               <p>A Good Prince can (without any grudge) obtain difficult matters, by impoſing mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate Taxes, when the neceſſity of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment requireth them, and afterwards, by remitting a great part of them, when his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:65868:14"/>ask for no Relief or Immunity from them, nor make any Complaint againſt them: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Prince, by ſo doing, doth ſufficiently manifeſt to them his Good-will and Clemency.</p>
               <p>Thus King <hi>Darius,</hi> the third from <hi>Cyrus,</hi> being to impoſe Taxes upon his Subjects, enquired of the Governours of his Provinces (together with other Queſtions) whether the Taxes were grievous and burdenſome? when they anſwered, That they were but moderate, he charg'd them that they ſhould exact but the half thereof. The Kings equity was ſuch, that he thought the half of that, which ſeemed moderate to his <hi>Princes,</hi> to be enough; yea, over and above. For he had rather win his People by Clemency, and Acts of grace, than by a rigid Superiorty to diſarm, weaken, and enſlave them.</p>
               <p>Thus a Tyrant (who is but the Ape of a King) when he intends to demand intollerable Things, and ſuck the very Blood of his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects (becauſe they ſhould never be in capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city to ſhake off the yoak of their Slavery) firſt of all impoſeth great Burdens, to the end he might afterwards ſeem to remitt and paſs off his own Right and Intereſt, and by that means act with the Clemency of a good King.</p>
               <p>You ſhall obtain what you deſire from one, by asking not directely, and at firſt
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:65868:14"/>daſh (if it be a hard thing, and that your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt may be denied;) but by this courſe you ſhall obtain it from one who is altogether averſe from your purpoſe.</p>
               <p>Firſt of all, ask very eagerly, ſomething that is harder to be obtain'd than what you deſign'd to ask; till, at Length, you get him to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe that he could rather grant any thing in the World. Then ask what you deſigned, and you ſhall obtain it, unleſs he has a mind to be worſe then his promiſe.</p>
               <p>Thus <hi>Scipio,</hi> when he would tranſlate the War into <hi>Africa,</hi> (to the end he might well accoutre his unarmed men) gave charge to the Nobles of <hi>Sicily,</hi> to accoutre themſelves moſt gallantly, as if they had been to go along with him. When they met together, the Nobles as earneſtly begg'd of him not to go, as if they had been unarmed Men. <hi>Give then</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>your Arms to my Souldiers;</hi> which they very rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily did, as <hi>Scipio</hi> would have had it.</p>
               <p>But if he, whom you Petition, ſhall ſwear he will not grant your Requeſt; Then you ſhall ask the quite Contrary to that which you reſolved to Petition for, at Firſt. Then when he ſhall turn his Vows and Proteſtations to the Contrary, you ſhall either obtain what you would have, elſe he ſhall be forſworn.</p>
               <p>Thus <hi>Anaximenes</hi> (when he had heard that <hi>Alexander the Great</hi> had ſworn to do the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:65868:15"/>quite Contrary to whatſoever he reqeſted of him) obtained Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to his <hi>Lampſacenians,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Nicolans Thomae lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>65.</hi> de var, Hiſt.</note> Firſt, deſiring that their <hi>City</hi> might be plundred, then overthrown, and then that the <hi>Citizens</hi> themſelves might be kill'd or ſold Slaves. By which wicked and cunning Counſel, the Victorious <hi>Alexander,</hi> was Van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhed, ſo that fearing the ſwelling Fury and irreconcileable Revenge, on both ſides, and dangerous Conſequences of what <hi>Anaximenes</hi> adviſed him to, he made up the ſuppoſed Breach, Reconcileing them (which was no hard mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to do) and proteſted, by an Oath, that he would never after, do any thing to the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice of the <hi>Lampſacenians.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE. VI.</hi> How to diſarm and weaken an Enemy.</head>
               <p>THE way to diſarm and weaken an Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, but eſpecially, to deprive him of his Friends, may be contrived ſeveral ways, whereof this is one,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> deal very friendly with your Enemy's Friend, and in your Enemy's preſence, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo before thoſe who inform your Enemy; and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:65868:15"/>ever now and then, with ſquinting Eyes (like thoſe who dread that all Things are not ſafe) gaze upon thoſe timorous Informers, as if you and they did on both ſides privately communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate theſe Secrets, which you would not have your Enemy to know of, ſo as thereby he may become leſs cautious; for nothing will move an obſerving Perſon, more than a caution counterfeited with great artifice and cunning.</p>
               <p>Thus <hi>Scipio,</hi> and the other <hi>Roman</hi> Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours, dealt with <hi>Hannibal,</hi> at <hi>Antiochus</hi> his Court; for, as often as King <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ochus</hi> fortun'd to come ſuddainly up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them,<note place="margin">Frontin. C. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note> they brought about, with their fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent and familiar Diſcourſes with <hi>Hannibal,</hi> what they mainly laboured for, <hi>viz.</hi> that he, who formerly was deſigned to be General of the Army, againſt the <hi>Romans,</hi> might be ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected of Treachery by the King, as favouring the <hi>Romans.</hi> The <hi>Roman Ambaſſadours</hi> made a Show as if they had come into <hi>Aſia</hi> to treat with <hi>Antiochus,</hi> concerning a Peace whilſt the chief intent of their Embaſſy (which they pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liated all along) was no other then to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Hannibal</hi> a ſuſpected Perſon to <hi>Antiochus;</hi> ſo that he might not be Truſted with an Army where with totally to over-throw the <hi>Romans.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> you ſhall render your Enemy's Friend a ſuſpected Perſon, if with Gifts and Preſents you ſend him Letters, written with
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:65868:16"/>the greateſt Friendſhip imaginable: adviſing him, in General Terms, to make good his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, which Letters muſt be intercepted, ſo as they may come to your Enemy's Hands. Thus when <hi>Quintus Metellus</hi>'s Letters written (with the greateſt Familiarity and Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction) to <hi>Jugurtha</hi>'s Friends;<note place="margin">Frontin. C. <hi>8.</hi>
                  </note> for betraying the King to <hi>Metellus,</hi> were intercep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: King <hi>Jugurtha</hi> inflicted a grievous puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment on them all; but afterwards, being (by this means) deprived both of Friends and good Councel, he was himſelf eaſily deſtroyed by the <hi>Romans.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> The Suſpicion will ſtill move, and more be encreaſed, if the Writing, on the out-ſide, reſemble a Hand different from the in-ſide.</p>
               <p>Thus, when the <hi>Syracuſians</hi> endeavoured, by the Conduct and Aſſiſtance of <hi>Dion,</hi> to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throne <hi>Dionyſius,</hi> who kept the Wives of a great many in Priſon in the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Potienus</hi> 4.</note> and amongſt the reſt, <hi>Hyppanio, Dion</hi>'s youngeſt Son. It was granted, privately, to ſome Women (<hi>Dionyſius</hi> conniving) to carry ſorrowful Letters, to their bemoaning Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands. But when he knew that (as ſuſpected Letters) they would be read in the publick Council of the Citizens, he privately convey'd in to the Number, his own Letter; the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward <hi>Inſcription</hi> of which did reſemble the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:65868:16"/>Hand, and bear the Name of <hi>Hippanio,</hi> to his Father <hi>Dion.</hi> But in the in-ſide, <hi>Dionyſius</hi> had written very friendly to <hi>Dion,</hi> as if they had been Confederate, to betray the <hi>Citizens</hi> at an appointed time. Theſe, with other things, being publickly read, <hi>Dion</hi> was looked upon as a perfidious <hi>Traitour</hi> and <hi>Villain</hi> by all the Grandees of <hi>Syracuſe;</hi> which was <hi>Dionyſius</hi>'s only Deſign, and that they might not have ſo brave a <hi>General,</hi> to work his overthrow.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> A Perſon may be rendered hateful to a People, if, by an exact Imitation, you contrive and counterfeit ſome pernitious project or evil Work (which will be ill taken by all) and then publiſh it in his Name.</p>
               <p>Thus <hi>Anaxemenes</hi> (who could counterfeit <hi>Theopompus</hi>'s Stile, publiſhed in his Name, Lyes, Fables, and Stories;<note place="margin">Pauſan. l. <hi>6.</hi>
                  </note> which diſgraced, and made him ſo infamous, all <hi>Greece</hi> over, that where ever he went he was ſtill in danger of his Life.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE VII.</hi> How to diſſemble.</head>
               <p>HE that would ſpeak one thing and think another, muſt be cautious that his
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:65868:17"/>Voice, Countenance, and Behaviour agree to the Senſe and Humour of his Diſcourſe, leſt his diſſembling be diſcovered, and he betray himſelf, and be ſuſpected. For, as the Nature of his Diſcourſe changeth, ſo alſo ought the Voice and Geſture of the Speaker to be altered too; as he that ſpeaks merrily ought to have one way of ſpeaking, and he that ſpeaks grave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly another, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> what is known to the vulgar hath alſo the vulgar report; but if you ſpeak of a modeſt Perſon, you may ſay <hi>he bluſhed,</hi> and therefore, the matter is ſure; if you ſpeak of a fearful Man, then with <hi>Virgil</hi>
               </p>
               <q>Obſtupuit; ſteierunt<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> comae, vox faucibus haeſit.</q>
               <q>
                  <l>Aſtoniſhed, his Hair up ſtood,</l>
                  <l>And could not utter bad or good.</l>
               </q>
               <p>So muſt one humour all Circumſtances of his Diſcourſe.</p>
               <p>Thus <hi>Hannibal,</hi> when a great many of his Souldiers left his Army, and went in to the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans;</hi> perceiving that the reſt, by that means,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Frontin.</hi> 3.18.</note> might be diſencou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged, and that ſtill more Spies did lurk in his Camps, to inform the <hi>Romans;</hi> and privately betray him, as far as their cowardly power went; that he might encourage his dejected Souldiers, and be revenged on the <hi>Deſerters</hi> or
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:65868:17"/>
                  <hi>Run-a-ways;</hi> in a Publick Council, and in the hearing of a great many of his Soldiers, with a Counterfeit, Chearful, Brazen-Face, he told, <hi>That they had not run away, but by the Perſuaſion of their Officers (as becometh Courageous Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers) gone to be Spies, and Diſcover the Strength and Deſigns of the Enemy; and that, in Battel, they might Surprize, and Seize them, behind their Backs.</hi> By this Fabulous Commendation, he encouraged his own Soldiers, but inflamed the <hi>Romans</hi> againſt the Deſerters; ſo that they did cut off their Right Hands, and ſent them back to <hi>Hannibal.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE. VIII.</hi> How to Perſuade and Diſſuade</head>
               <p>YOU ſhall perſuade one of little Spirit to undertake great and hard Matters; to proſecute that which he taketh to be good and pleaſing, and diſſuade him from that Evil which he looketh on as leſs Dangerous; if, by ſome moving Object, you raiſe in him a violent Paſſion, as Wrath, Fear, Hatred, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For then the vehement Paſſion augmenteth the Strength and Vitals of the Mind, to proſecute
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:65868:18"/>and perform a Memorable Act; the attempt whereof, might otherways prove but in vain, for want of Vigour, Courage, and Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanimity.</p>
               <p>Thus<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Horat.</hi> 2. <hi>Sat.</hi> 3.</note> 
                  <hi>Opimius</hi> the Miſer, could not, by any Remedy, be cured of his <hi>Lethargy,</hi> till the Phyſician (to keep him awake by ſome Anxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Care, and paſſionate Apprehenſion) told him, <hi>That his Heirs did contrive how to take away, and rob him of his Money; and therefore, deſired him to Cauſe all his Treaſure to be brought to his Chamber, in his Sight, that with a Careful Eye, he might ſecure it from the Hands of his Covetous Heirs.</hi> By which means the Phyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an obtained his End: For the Miſer <hi>Opimius,</hi> having ſo Covetous a Deſire after his Money, that he could not Sleep, (ſtill keeping his Eye upon his Treaſure,) was by his Watchfulneſs cured of his <hi>Lethargy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By this means alſo the brute Beaſts may be induced to obey their Maſters Deſires.<note n="‖" place="margin">Comp. l. <hi>7.</hi> c. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note> For <hi>Brachius,</hi> the <hi>Peruſian General,</hi> when, neither by Whip nor Spur, he could cauſe his weary Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to take the Mountains, in purſuit of his Enemy; out of the Spoil and Herd which he had taken, choſe young luſty Mares, and ſet them in the Front of his Cavalry, which ſo animated and ſtirred up his wearied Horſes, that there was more difficulty to keep them back, than drive them forwards.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:65868:18"/>Yet all are not ſtirred up by the ſame Excite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, by reaſon of the variety of Natures, Manners, and Education: Therefore it is carefully to be conſidered, how, and by what means, ſuch and ſuch Perſons ought to be dealt with; and (conform to the Diſpoſitions of thoſe with whom you are to deal;) to change and uſe Excitements, Arguments and Strate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gems of Wit, Policy, and Diſcretion.</p>
               <p>Thus<note n="†" place="margin">Curt. l. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Alexander the Great,</hi> when he went out to Battel, againſt <hi>Darius,</hi> he ſtirred up his Soldiers by Excitements of diverſe Natures: <hi>Firſt,</hi> The <hi>Macedonians,</hi> (whom he knew to be Ambitious of Honour,) to give an evident Demonſtration of their Valour, for obtaining the prize of an Univerſal Empire. The <hi>Grae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians,</hi> (deſirous of Liberty,) that they would be revenged on the <hi>Perſians,</hi> and make them bear the Yoak of their Slavery, as long as they had done theirs. The <hi>Illyrians</hi> and <hi>Thracians,</hi> (who lived by Theft and Rapine) he perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to Magnanimity, by ſetting before them a great Spoil, and Rich Booty.</p>
               <p>An Honeſt Mind can be diſſuaded from a wicked Deſign, by ſetting open the Shame and Infamy of the Action intended. * Thus the <hi>Mileſian</hi> Virgins, who (as Authors write) were taken with ſuch a ſtrange and unheard of Madneſs, that almoſt in every Houſe of the City ſome hang'd themſelves, without any
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:65868:19"/>known Cauſe; and could not be cured of their Malady, nor be diſſuaded from Self-Murther, by the Perſuaſions and Arguments of the Wiſe, nor the Tears of their Parents; but were rather made worſe, and ſet more on edge; till the <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> ordained, <hi>That the Firſt who ſhould hang her ſelf, ſhould be dragg'd naked (by the Heels) through the Streets of the City, and hung up in the Market Place, as a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nument of Shame, Infamy, and Diſgrace:</hi> Which ſtruck ſuch a Terrour in the Minds of the young Virgins, that never one of them after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards did attempt any violence againſt her ſelf.</p>
               <p>Thus alſo <hi>Selenicus,</hi> the Law-giver, made the Women and Ladies of <hi>Locris</hi> to forbear their gorgeous and gawdy Apparel, and their great Convoys, by theſe Laws: He ordained, <hi>That no Lady or Matron ſhould have above one Attendent, or Page, to attend her, unleſs ſhe would acknowledge her ſelf firſt, in face of the Council, a great Drunkard; and that none ſhould wear Ribbons, Top-knots, Chains, or Bracelets,</hi> &amp;c. but when ſhe went a Whoring, that with her fine Apparel and wanton Dreſs, ſhe might allure her Gallants to her Bed of Pleaſure. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other ſuch Law was in <hi>Syracuſe,</hi> viz. That no Woman ſhould wear any gorgeous and gawdy Apparel, till firſt ſhe ſhould acknowledge her ſelf a Whore.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:65868:19"/>If you would diſſuade an obſtinate Perſon from an Error, you muſt ſhew it to him in a Parallel, to make him ſenſible, and convince him of it; for, if he can be brought to a ſenſe thereof, you have done the work: ſince none will Err willingly, nor perſiſt in an Error, when he knows it to be an Error. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, ſhew him his miſtake, with a chearful counterfeit conſent, by bringing him to the firſt original and riſe of his Error; or, more ſharply moving him with the bad Conſequences and Evils that will follow, if he perſiſt in ſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious an Opinion and Enterprize.</p>
               <p>But to diſſuade one from a pernicious De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, whom clear Arguments, and evident De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrations cannot convince, but make more obſtinate, theſe Meaſures muſt be taken. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a wheedling manner, condeſcend to his Deſigns, as if they were very pleaſing and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional, and as you were altogether of his Mind. Then take a full Information of all the draught and drift of his Intentions, as if you were in Love with his Phancies, and intended them for a Rule to practiſe by, or uſe them as Arguments to ſatisfie and convince another, who ſtrove to diſſuade you from ſuch a Project. Then ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain to him all his plauſible Arguments, as you highly approved of them; but in ſuch a plain manner, and ſuch terms, as may make the weakneſs of them appear, and he may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:65868:20"/>to ſuſpect his Subſtantial Fabrick to be but a perverted Maggot of imaginary Phancies. Then ſtart ſome Arguments, which may be objected againſt his Concluſions, and make for a contrary Opinion, confuting them at ſuch a ſlight rate, as he may eaſily perceive them to be ſtronger than any he can bring for the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of the contrary Opinion, which he ſo much dandleth and approveth of.</p>
               <p>Thus <hi>Bacovius</hi> the <hi>Calabrian,</hi> hunting after greater Preferment, and aſpiring to higher Dignity, (though he was the chief Magiſtrate in <hi>Capua,</hi>) took theſe Meaſures, to ingratiate himſelf in the Favour of the <hi>Senators,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hermog. Lib. <hi>4.</hi> de invent. <hi>13.</hi> Plin. Lib. <hi>23.</hi>
                  </note> and ſave them alive, when the common People had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded to cut them off, and commit the Rule of the Government wholly to him: <hi>Firſt,</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving given the <hi>Senators</hi> a Secret Oath of Fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, he impriſoried them in the Senate-Houſe. Then called up the Commons to a Common-Council, where he made a ſhew of giving up the Senators to them, in theſe Words. <hi>That which you have ſo often deſired and wiſhed for, ye Men of</hi> Capua, <hi>that it might be in your Power to be avenged of this wicked</hi> Senate, <hi>now you have; and them all (and that without tumult or danger) ſhut up in Priſon, by my means, in the</hi> Senate-Houſe. <hi>Take them unarmed, ſeverally by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and diſpoſe of them according to your Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:65868:20"/>Yet leſt we ſhould do any thing raſhly, through ſpite or malice, be perſuaded that, by all means, it is neceſſary, before ye cut off this miſchievous Senate, to chuſe a new one, that is far better for your purpoſe, unleſs you have a mind to enſlave your ſelves to the Arbitrary Government of one ſingle Perſon: Go on therefore, and let us not delay, but put this Courſe in Execution, with ſpeed: Let every</hi> Senator <hi>be ſeverally brought before you, and paſs Sentence on every one of them; and then nominate, and bring in a better, in the room of each one that is to dye: For it is in your Power to execute Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, and condemn thoſe you find Guilty; and to chooſe better in their room. Therefore go on de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberately, and with all ſpeed, reward theſe wicked Senators according to their Deſervings.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Deſign pleaſed them well; but when they proceeded to the Examination of the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nators apart, and had compared them with thoſe they had newly elected, (which were to be put in their rooms,) they perceived the meanneſs and ignoble Circumſtances of thoſe ill-bred ſtartups: Foraſmuch as they were, for the moſt part, poor, beggerly, and unskilful in the management of publick Affairs. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon they judged it more adviſed to continue the Old Senate. <hi>Then</hi> (ſays <hi>Bacovius</hi>) <hi>ſeeing you cannot be without a</hi> Senate, <hi>nor can find a better than what at preſent you have, you had bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter reſtore the impriſoned</hi> Senators <hi>to their former
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:65868:21"/>Dignities, and be reconciled to them; to the end they may be more ſerviceable to you for the future, than bring the City to Confuſion and Ruine, by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priving it of all Government.</hi> And ſo forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they agreed thereto, and by this did <hi>Baco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vius</hi> gain to himſelf great Favour, and Prehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minence without ſtroke of Sword.</p>
               <p>If <hi>Bacovius</hi> had, at firſt, imperiouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, that the People muſt have bore with the <hi>Senate,</hi> becauſe a new one would have been more mean and ignoble than what they had; without all peradventure, he would have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten in the People a greater rancour and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlike to the <hi>Senators;</hi> they being ſo much alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy incenſed againſt them. Thus, according to <hi>Bacovius</hi>'s Method, the incenſed Vulgar, or Rabble of Common-People, (when they are in an Errour of Judging all others, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be convinced by rational Arguments, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out danger of making the matter worſe,) ought to be humoured and wrought upon, by what is more pleaſing and acceptable, to rectifie their miſtake.</p>
               <p>Thus <hi>Machiavel</hi> argueth, <hi>If the wicked Old</hi> Senate <hi>muſt be cut off, and a better New One Choſe from among the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lib. 6: Diſp. Cap. 43.</note> 
                  <hi>let the People, firſt, argue thus with themſelves: Either this or that, or ſome Third Fellow of the Rabble, is better and fitter for Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment than he who is to be caſt off: But nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:65868:21"/>this, nor that, nor the third, nor another of the Rabble, can be choſen better and fitter for Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, (the People themſelves being Judges,) therefore it is not convenient, upon any Account, to alter the</hi> Senate, <hi>or to change it for a New One.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Moreover, there is a two-fold Perſuaſion; one in direct and plain terms, which tells plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as it means; and there is another which comes by Inſinuations, Far-fetches, and ſome ſubtile Contrivance of a Man's own Fancy.</p>
               <p>Thus a certain poor Man had for his ſworn Enemy a great and rich Man, who proferred, in a time of great Famine, to keep the City where the poor Man lived, if the Citizens would give him up (the poor Man) to be put to Death. The poor Man ſuſpecting, and fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the inconſtancy of the unſtable Multitude, and queſtioning the Honeſty of the Hunger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtarv'd <hi>Rabble,</hi> durſt not hazard directly to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuade them from conſenting to the unjuſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of the Rich Man, nor argue that an Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Perſon ſhould not be put to Death, leſt he ſhould the more provoke their Inclinations, to give him up. Therefore, by Inſinuations, and a far-fetched ſober Contrivance, to mollifie their Hearts, he made his humble Addreſs to them thus:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Verily, for my own part, I refuſe not to dye for the Good and Preſervation of my Country; altho
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:65868:22"/>nothing worthy or deſerving Death be found in me. However, dear and honeſt Citizens, conſider firſt, whether he hath Corn enough to anſwer the price of my Blood; and then (if he have) whether or not an honeſt kind Citizen, who is able, be not bound to aſſiſt his Fellow Citizens, without the Effuſion of Innocent Blood. And Thirdly, whether or not the Common-wealth can juſtly, in time of neceſſity, take all the uſeleſs Corn, for the maintenance of ſtarved poor People, paying the juſt worth, from one who will not part with it, under the ſatisfying of his undeſerved Revenge, and the price of Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Blood. Now conſider, whether you can more freely ſeize his Corn, than conſent to ſo horrid a Murther.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus alſo, when the <hi>Lacedemonians</hi> deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of the <hi>Athenians,</hi> (who deſired an eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Peace,) that <hi>Pericles</hi> ſhould firſt be given up to them. <hi>Pericles,</hi> conſidering with himſelf that he would be ſafer, and more beloved a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the People, and could prevail more by counterfeiting and declaring a willing and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Reſolution to dye for the ſafety of the Common-Wealth, than by openly contradict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Senate,</hi> adviſed the <hi>Senatours</hi> to give himſelf up to the <hi>Lacedemonians,</hi> and to hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to a Lawleſs Neceſſity, ſince the State of Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs ſo required; but with ſuch Arguments as did very plainly manifeſt how Slaviſh and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proachful a thing it was, for any Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:65868:22"/>to obey ſuch unreaſonable and imperious an Enemy.</p>
               <p>In like manner King <hi>Philip,</hi> the Father of <hi>Alexander the Great,</hi> after he had, with a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of aſſerting Liberty, invaded a great part of <hi>Greece,</hi> at length beſieged <hi>Athens;</hi> but, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, did cunningly excuſe himſelf, that he did not at firſt think of waging War againſt the <hi>Senate,</hi> and People of <hi>Athens,</hi> and that they ſhould ſoon be reſcued from war, from the Siege, and from Famine; if they would only deliver him up Ten of the greateſt of their <hi>Orators;</hi> who indeed were his greateſt Enemies, and never gave over their barking and bawling againſt him in their <hi>Senate.</hi> The People judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it beſt, that a few of their <hi>Oratours,</hi> for the ſafety of many, ſhould be given up; <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſthenes</hi> perſuaded them to the contrary Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, by diſcovering to them King <hi>Philip</hi>'s craft, and double-hand Dealings, by this Fable. <hi>Of old</hi> (ſays he) <hi>the Wolf offered Peace to the Sheep, on Condition, the Doggs ſhould be deſtroyed, whom he did accuſe, as the Authors and Promotors of all their Contentions and Diſcord. But the Doggs (thoſe watchful and careful Creatures, who ſtill gave notice to the Sheep of the Wolfes approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) being took out of the way, the Treacherous Wolf, as often as he liſted, without fear of Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or reſpect to his former Proteſtations, made havock of the poor harmleſs deluded Sheep: Even
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:65868:23"/>ſo</hi> Philip <hi>requireth us to be delivered up, who diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover his enſnaring Policy, and Treacherous Plots; and withſtand his Force, by animating you all to quit your ſelves, in your Vindications, as becometh valiant Men; that by this means he may deprive the City of it's Keepers and Watchmen, and deſtroy it unawares without difficulty.</hi> Now the whole drift of his Diſcourſe was good and honeſt, <hi>viz.</hi> that the Oratours ſhould no more be given up to King <hi>Philip,</hi> than the Doggs to the <hi>Wolfe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But when you drive at one thing, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign another, contrary meaſures muſt be taken; as if you intended indirectly, and at a diſtance, to perſuade one to a ſober Life; go on thus,</p>
               <p>Grant me only theſe few rational Requeſts; be not mad drunk after Twelve a Clock at Night, leſt you diſquiet People in their reſt; and becauſe you <hi>cannot</hi> forbear your Old Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits of Drinking, running about, emptying your Belly at both ends, and committing other ſuch baſe Acts of Indecency, as are not fit to be mentioned; begin your walks about Seven a Clock in the Morning, that you may finiſh them about Twelve at Night; for by that time you may be wearied, and leave off to moleſt, and be troubleſom to others.</p>
               <p>But if a Perſon obſtinately ſtill perſiſt in his Opinion, after his Error hath been clearly (and in a friendly way) ſhown to him, do him ſome
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:65868:23"/>injury, which may more clearly demonſtrate his miſtake; which injury, <hi>according</hi> to his own <hi>Opinion</hi> (that he ſo confidently affirmeth and maintaineth) can, by clear Conſequence, be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to be no injury at all, tho he ſhould bring it to a Tryal of Law. Thus the obſtinate Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niator will be forced either to condemn his own falſe Opinion, or acknowledg that he hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived no injury. After this manner, one, that maintained that all things came by Contingency, overthrew the Opinion of him, who believed that all things came by Fate. He gave him a Blow under the Ear, and when the Cauſe came to a Tryal at Law, he cleared himſelf thus. <hi>Ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I ſtruck you this Blow, driven to it by ſome fatal neceſſity, or by chance, and of my own free-Will. If caſually and by chance, then by this I prove there is given free-Will and Contingency: Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in this Caſe, have I done him any wrong, but have convinced him of his Errour, and brought him to an acknowledgment of the Truth, which (perhaps) was my Deſign, and for which he ought not to accuſe, but reward me, and give me thanks. But if I be driven, by ſome fatal neceſſity, to do you this injury, and give you ſo violent a Blow under the Ear, than I am ſtill clear; for who can withſtand Fate, when, of neceſſity, he muſt ſubmit?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="part">
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:65868:24"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE IX.</hi> How to obtain what you Deſire, without danger of loſing the Favour of him whom you deſire it of.</head>
               <p>IF you would ask for any thing of one, whoſe Favour you fear to loſe, and whoſe Wrath you fear thereby to incur (if your Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition ſhould be ill taken) go on after this Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod. Firſt, conſider whether you have rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to fear, that you will come off with reproof and repulſe, from him whom you petition; and therefore dares not hazard to be ſo bold, though, otherways, he be both familiar and kind. Then, when you have weighed theſe things ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly in your Mind, counterfeit that another asketh that of you, or of ſome other Perſon, which you really deſign to ask of him. Then take his Advice, whether it be not unworthy and baſe, to ask ſuch a thing of a Friend; and if he judge it neither baſe nor irrational, then, without any farther delay, you may down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right ask what you deſign, and you ſhall ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain it. But if he repute the demand baſe and irrational, deſiſt from your Intention, if you
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:65868:24"/>would continue in his Favour; for what a Man thinketh not unworthy to be asked of another, he will not take ill if asked of himſelf.</p>
               <p>This was <hi>Euraſtritus</hi>'s Practice, when he deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gned to know whether <hi>Seleucus</hi> would counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance the inordinate Love of his Son <hi>Antiochus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Plutarch. in Deme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trio, Suidas, Plin. Lib. <hi>29.</hi> Cap. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> which he had for his Mother-in-Law, <hi>Stratonice,</hi> for whom he was fallen Sick, and ready to Dye: Which the Phyſician found out, whilſt he could find him troubled with no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Diſtemper; for, as he felt his Pulſe (<hi>Stra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonice</hi> paſſing by) he obſerved the motion of his Veins alter, and turn more violent in their Courſe; and a ſudden change, and cold ſweat ſurprize the Face of <hi>Antiochus.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, <hi>Euraſtritus</hi> ſpoke to his Father thus, <hi>Your Son is a dead Man; for, he hath paſſionately fallen in Love with my Wife, and will never recover, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs he obtain his Deſire, which I am reſolved ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to agree to.</hi> Whereupon King <hi>Seleucus,</hi> with inordinate and compaſſionate Tears, (as a Favour never to be forgotten,) requeſted <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſtritus</hi> to comply and ſave his Son's Life, by granting his Deſire. <hi>Do not you</hi> (anſwered <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſtritus</hi>) <hi>demand that of me, which no Man in reaſon can demand?</hi> To which the King made anſwer: <hi>I heartily wiſh he had fallen in love with my</hi> Stratonice. <hi>Do you ſay ſo ſeriouſly?</hi> (repli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Euraſtritus.</hi>) <hi>Yes, truly,</hi> (ſays the King,) <hi>as
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:65868:25"/>I wiſh the Fates to favour me. Then</hi> (anſwered <hi>Euraſtritus</hi>) <hi>you neither ſtand in need of me, nor my Wife; for you can cure him your ſelf: And if you will let him enjoy the company of your</hi> Strato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice, <hi>he will ſoon recover.</hi> His Father, King <hi>Seleucus,</hi> gave him his own Wife, and after a while, the young Man recovered. And leſt this ſhould have been known, and given offence to the People, <hi>Seleucus</hi> ſtill ſpoke to the Young Man's Commendation, which was very profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the Commonwealth, though the Thing, in it ſelf, was far contrary both to Cuſtom and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE. X.</hi> How to obtain what you Deſire, when the Perſon whom you deſire it of is alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether averſe.</head>
               <p>IF you would obtain what you deſire, when the Perſon of whom you ask it is abſolutely averſe from granting it, you muſt make that which you requeſt hateful, or appear hurtful or dangerous in his Eyes, and then afterwards you may cautiouſly ask and obtain. Thus, a Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant in <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> deſirons to buy a Houſe
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:65868:25"/>of his next Neighbour, which his Neighbour was not willing to ſell, cauſed ſuch a formida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble noiſe to be heard, every Night, in the Houſe, that all the Neighbourhood thought it had been frequented with Evil Spirits, which he brought about after this manner. The Houſe being neareſt to his own, he pulled a Stone out of that place of the Wall which was concealed by a Desk, and through it, every Night, he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed an Iron Bullet, tyed to a ſtring, by which he drew it too and fro, over the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants; whereat they were ſo frightned that the Landlord was glad to part with the Houſe, at any rate.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE. XI.</hi> How to force a Confeſſion from one who is obſtinate.</head>
               <p>HE that would, by Circumvention, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce one to confeſs that which (down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right and directly) he will not, muſt be accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed as guilty of ſome greater Crime, relating ſo near to that which you would have him con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, that the acknowledging of the leſſer will clear him of the greater. Thus a certain Prieſt, deſirous to bring one to confeſs his long abſence
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:65868:26"/>from Church, and receiving the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> did ſubornate thoſe that did accuſe him, that (in the time of the Prieſts abſence) when others were at Prayers, he prophaned the conſecrated Things, and threw Stones at the holy <hi>Images.</hi> Thus the poor Man, being afraid of a greater Puniſhment, was fore'd to acknowledg his long abſence from Church.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE XII.</hi> How to force any thing from One, by that which he moſt hateth.</head>
               <p>YOU ſhall force a thing from One, that is unwilling to grant it, by over perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding him that it is your Right, or by driving him to that which he moſt abhorreth. Thus a poor, but ingenious young Man, whilſt he was put to the utmoſt point of neceſſity, and knew not how to live, heard of a certain rich Godly <hi>Merchant,</hi> that could not endure an Oath, to whom he went, and pretended that he owed him a large Sum of Money; but the Merchant denying, was brought to a Tryal of Law, by the young Man, who deſired him to clear him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf by his Oath. But the Merchant choſe ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to pay the Money, which he owed not
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:65868:26"/>than ſwear. The young Man, having gotten the Mony, fell a trading, and grew rich; and after a few years, returned to the <hi>Merchant,</hi> from whom he had forced the Money, and pay'd him both Stock and Intereſt; beging his Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on, humbly acknowledging his Offence, and that then he was driven to the utmoſt point of neceſſity, and knew not how to live. The Merchant, weighing the young Man's Honeſty and Ingenuity, did not only forgive him, but alſo gave him his only Daughter, with a large Portion.</p>
               <p>This happened well on both ſides; but oft-times, in ſuch Caſes, the Effect and Proof makes the Contrivance good or bad, wiſe or fooliſh: For had this young Man loſt by his Trading, and not improved the Money, (which, very unjuſtly, he cheated the Merchant of,) he had not been able to reſtore it again; and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, by the reſult, had been (deſervedly) reputed a Rogue to his Grave. Therefore, I ſay, it is dangerous to take ſuch dubious Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, unleſs in Caſes of great Neceſſity: For the worſt ſometimes may anſwer Expectation, when at other times, the beſt will not.</p>
               <p>I heard a Story, much like this, of an <hi>Engliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man;</hi> which was thus: A broken <hi>Gold-Smith,</hi> in <hi>London,</hi> obſerved a rich <hi>Graſier</hi> receive Two Hundred Pounds, whereof he rob'd him, as he was on his way homeward. About Seven
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:65868:27"/>Years after, he met the <hi>Graſier,</hi> by chance, in the Street; whom he, very kindly, invited home to his Houſe; where he profer'd to pay him the Two Hundred Pounds, with Intereſt. But the <hi>Graſier,</hi> not minding the time when the Money was lent, took the proſer for a jeer or ſome deſigned trap; till the <hi>Gold Smith</hi> told him of the time and place, concealing the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon who had committed the Robbery. The <hi>Graſier</hi> was, at laſt, perſuaded to receive his Money, but was ſo civil as to take no Intereſt; but was very curious to know the Perſon to whom he had ſo long lent it, proteſting that he would do him no diskindneſs, but rather any Favour that lay in his Power. The <hi>Gold-Smith,</hi> told him, <hi>Sir, I have a Child to be Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtened to morrow, and if you pleaſe to ſtay and be God Father, the Perſon that did you this injury will be preſent, and make his Apology, for detain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your Mony ſo long.</hi> The <hi>Graſier</hi> was well ſatisfied; and (when all was over) the Gold-Smith told him that he was the Perſon himſelf, to whom he had ſo long lent his Mony; and that mere neceſſity, contrary to his Inclination, forced him to it; and that he had kept him out of Priſon, and given him whereupon to live honeſtly in the World. Whereupon, the rich <hi>Graſier</hi> was ſo well pleaſed, and ſo much taken with the <hi>Goldſmith</hi>'s Wit, Honeſty, and Inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuity,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:65868:27"/>that he gave the 200 <hi>pounds</hi> to his God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, as a Confirmation of his durable Reſpects. The Reſult was good, though many on ſuch Meaſures, have gotten a Halter for their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</p>
               <p>There is no ſurer way, to obtain what you Deſire, than by giving the Perſon, whom you deſign to ask, ſome ground to think that you can do him ſome great Favour, for many have been ſo forward, on ſuch an Occaſion, as to ſtudy how to ingratiate themſelves in the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of the Perſon, of whom they reckoned to receive a Kindneſs. Thus a brisk Spark (who had more confidence than Mony, and wanted to be treated) came to a rich Gold-Smith, and asked him what a Wedge of Gold, of ſuch a length, might be worth, making a Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration on his Arm. The Gold-Smith ſuſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting that he himſelf had ſuch an one to ſell, was deſirous to ſee it, telling that he never ſaw one ſo large. The young Man, as if he had come by it ſome unlawful way, to confirm the Gold-Smith in his Opinion, and ſet him more on edge, began to ſmother the Diſcourſe, as afraid to ſpeak of ſo rich a Booty, leſt it ſhould be inquired, how he came by it. The Gold-Smith, deſirous to pump him, took him to the Tavern, where, after ſeveral Bottles of Wine, the Gold-Smith, very ſeriouſly, asked if he could let him ſee the Wedge of Gold. <hi>Truly,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:65868:28"/>Sir,</hi> (replied the young Spark) <hi>I never, hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto, was Maſter of a Wedge of Gold, nor ever heard of one ſo large, as what I ſpoke to you of, at your Shop. But, I aſſure you, Sir, if any ſuch come to my Hand, you ſhall have the firſt profer of it, whether you buy it or not.</hi> The Gold-Smith, who formerly had been tranſported in Expectation, began to find out where he was; and after he was Maſter of his right Senſes, paid the Recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, wiſhed his Chapman a good Market, and ſo took leave. Another of his Trade, who had ſome Information of his Neighbour's Pren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, that the Gold-Smith had met with a rich accidental Booty, asked him, as he was a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming in to his Shop, if he ſhould go halfs. <hi>You ſhall have it all</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>if you will; what is the Matter?</hi> (replied the other?) <hi>The young Spark, that is at the Tavern</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>hath the largeſt Wedge of Gold, to ſell, that ever you ſaw, but we cannot agree.</hi> Whereupon, the other Gold-Smith haſtened to the Tavern, (where the young Gentleman was examining the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder of the Wine, which his Merchant had left him) and with a Covetuous Grace, in a moment, became very familiar and complaiſant, with the young Man; telling him what his Neighbour had told him, concerning the Wedge of Gold. The Spark (to Humour the Fancy) made as if he had been afraid to ſpeak of it, in a Tavern: Whereupon, the Gold-Smith took
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:65868:28"/>him home to his Houſe; and, after Dinner, brought about his Diſcourſe, concerning the Wedge of Gold; but finding the young Blade averſe from his purpoſe, ſet his Daughter a pumping of him, with her guilded Diſcourſe, and pleaſing Complements. But he, being too cunning for her Sex, told her Father, that he had diſpoſed of his Gold to his Neighbour, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he came, but could ſave him 1000 pound in his Pocket. The Old Man began to lend an attentive Ear, and called for another Bottle, which they drank out very Cordially; the ſmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling young Lady, now and then reliſhing the Glaſs with the perfume of her Lips; till the impatient Old Man could bear no longer, but would know how to ſave 1000 pounds. The young Spark told him; <hi>Sir, I hear that you have profer'd this young handſome Lady, your Daughter, to Wife to Mr.</hi> Frontinick, <hi>with</hi> 3000 <hi>pound, and I will take her with Two; and by this means, you may ſave</hi> 1000 <hi>pound in your Pocket.</hi> Both the Father and Daughter ſeem'd to be well pleaſed with the Jeſt; but the Old Man was in a Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and went to ſcold his Neighbour, for help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him to ſuch a Merchant, leaving the young couple in his Chamber; where they made ſo good uſe of their time, and became ſo inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate and loving with one another, that, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Father's Knowledge, the Lady was forc'd to go to Church, and Marry the young
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:65868:29"/>Spark. But the old Gentleman ſav'd nothing by it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE XIII.</hi> How to ſearch out another's Secrets.</head>
               <p>IF you would find out the Secrets of another, you muſt feign to him that one hath infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med you of ſuch Things; or rather ſuborn one to whiſper you, ſeriouſly, in the Ear, in his preſence, as Informers uſe to do. Then (af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter you have given him a reward for his Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation) ſay, that you have found out a few things concerning ſuch and ſuch a Matter; and that you are yet Ignorant of ſome particular Circumſtances, which (in time) you may come to know. Then the other being perſuaded that the greateſt part of his Secrets are found out, (and, therefore, that it is but in vain to conceal the reſt) will, of his own accord, diſcover the whole <hi>Intrigue,</hi> to keep or gain Favour, and to come the better off.</p>
               <p>Thus <hi>Dionyſius</hi> ſerved <hi>Andron.</hi> For, having truſted him with his Affairs, his Kinſman <hi>Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mocrates</hi> perſuaded <hi>Andron</hi> to deliver him up the Caſtle and Treaſury,<note place="margin">Aelianns, Lib. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note> thinking <hi>Dionyſius</hi>'s Abſence a fit op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:65868:29"/>to throw off the yoke of his Slavery But the Deſign not taking, <hi>Dionyſius</hi> returned in a ſhort ſpace, knowing nothing of <hi>Hermo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates</hi> his Project, by <hi>Andron,</hi> or any other In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>former. Notwithſtanding, being Jealous, that (in his Abſence) the Citizens might have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned ſome Plot, for the recovery of their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Liberty, he feign'd, as if he had been in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed of all the Factions, and Conſpiracies, which they had been contriving againſt him, in his abſence, and who was the chief Man that laid hold on the opportunity, and carried on the Deſign. <hi>Andron</hi> being (by this Fictitious Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy) deceived, (to ſave his own Bacon,) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray'd <hi>Hermocrates,</hi> by revealing all the Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſactions that had paſt betwixt them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE XIV.</hi> How to find out One's Secrets, by inſinua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting with another, who is privy to them.</head>
               <p>IF you would know a Secret which another will not reveal, you muſt wheedle him, by himſelf, to be ſerious in Diſcourſe; and then learn ſome other Secret, which he feareth not to make known: Then, without delay, go to
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:65868:30"/>his Crony, and intimate Friend (if he have any) who knoweth both the Secrets, and pretend that he hath told you the Secret which you are a fiſhing for; and, that you may perſuade him to believe you, tell him the other Secret which he told you. Then he (hearing this Secret revealed) will be convinced that the other is diſcovered too; therefore will not think it worth while to conceal that which is already known; but talk to you of it, as if you knew of it as well as himſelf. Thus (amongſt the <hi>Turks</hi>) a very dark Caſe in Law, was cleared and diſcuſſed by a very juſt Sentence.</p>
               <p>A certain Man, named <hi>Conſio,</hi> left a bag of Money in his Friend's Cuſtody; and, when he demanded it again, his Friend deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it,<note place="margin">Arod. Decret. lib. <hi>1.</hi> Tit. <hi>30.</hi>
                  </note> telling him that he had no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of his, and that he owed him not one Farthing, threatning him, that (if he ſcandaliz'd, and troubled him with ſuch idle and diſgraceful Diſcourſe) he would complain to the <hi>Emperour,</hi> thinking, thereby, to frighten the poor Man from asking after his Money; but all would not do; and the Action was at laſt brought before the <hi>Grand Seignior,</hi> who examined both the Parties, and checked him, in whoſe Hands the Money was left. But he (as he had been honeſt and clear from ſo baſe and wicked a Crime) deny'd the other's Accuſation, with a great deal of counterfeit
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:65868:30"/>Grief, and Trouble. But the other ſtood ſtifly to his point, confirming his Aſſertion, with un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feign'd Tears, and Demonſtrations of unſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kable Sorrow. The <hi>Emperour,</hi> deſirous to find out the truth of the Matter, delay'd his Sentence till another day; and then, underhand, ſent one privately, to him who had the Money, and, after a friendly and familiar way, adviſed him to reſtore it, and put an end to the Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, to ſave his Credit and Reputation; and ſaid that the <hi>Emperour</hi> might have bad thoughts of him, and that be might come off at a loſs. But he ſtill ſtood obſtinate, and would ſubmit to no Counſel or Arbitration. Wherefore the <hi>Emperour</hi> was concerned, and commanded the Debate to be diſcuſſed by none but himſelf, and, without delay, unawares, call'd them both before him. Then taking him who had the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney aſide, he asked if he lay with his Wife laſt Night, and whether he had done ſomething elſe, and at what Hour of the Night he did it. Then after he had come to a knowledge of theſe Secrets, he immediately ſent one to his Wife, to ſay, that her Husband deſired her to ſend him the bag of Money, which he gave her to keep; and if ſhe would not believe, to tell her (as Tokens) what her Husband had, ſecretly, told him. His Wife being convinc'd by theſe Secrets, (which none knew but her Husband and ſhe,) ſent the Money, and ſo the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guery
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:65868:31"/>was found out: And the <hi>Emperour</hi> did not only make him pay double, what he had defrauded <hi>Conſio</hi> of, but alſo took off his Head, to ſave himſelf from trouble, and make him Honeſt for the future.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE. XV.</hi> How to induce One to confeſs all his Secret Faults.</head>
               <p>IF you would allure one to confeſs all his Crimes and Secret Faults, you muſt catch him with an inevitable neceſſity of confeſſing; and you your ſelf muſt firſt begin, and confeſs your own Crimes, whether true or falſe no mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, for either will ſerve to ſhew him Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample.</p>
               <p>Thus <hi>Nelius,</hi> the Son of <hi>Codrus,</hi> the laſt King of the <hi>Athenians,</hi> when beat from his Kingdoms, he was (by Storms and Tempeſts at Sea) driven to <hi>Naxos,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Aelian. Lib. <hi>8.</hi> Cap. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note> whence he could not looſe, till he purged his Army from all profligate Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lains, and vile Perſons, as the <hi>Sooth-Sayers</hi> told him. But he, not knowing the good from the bad, appointed a general Confeſſion; and he
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:65868:31"/>(to allure the reſt, and induce them to a free and reſolute confeſſing of all their Crimes) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed firſt a great many Fictitious, Villanous Deeds, whereof he was not guilty, as that he had murdered a Boy, forc'd ſo many Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> By which Fiction he did induce all his Men to confeſs their ſecret Villanies, taking Example from their Maſter's Sins. Then, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving all the great and Bloody Sinners in <hi>Naxos,</hi> he ſail'd, with the leſſer, to <hi>Iönia,</hi> where they ſettled; and firſt of all, in <hi>Miletus.</hi> Now from thoſe afterwards, the other Eleven Cities of <hi>Iö<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia</hi> (which by that means came to be <hi>Athenian</hi> Colonies) had their riſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE XVI.</hi> How to find out the Secrets of Drunken Men.</head>
               <p>YOU may know whether the Speeches of a Drunken Man be reſolutely ſpoken, or raſhly, without any reſolvedneſs, if you pry into the Conſtitution, Nature, and Inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Drunkard; and obſerve whether he ſpeaks warily, or talketh idly whatever falleth in his Head: If he ſpeaks warily, then
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:65868:32"/>he ſpeaks adviſedly, and in earneſt, and his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe ought to be minded: But if his Tongue talk Nonſenſe, and run beyond Rational Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception, and ſpeak nothing to purpoſe, his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe is raſh, and only the effect of his Drunk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enneſs, and not worth taking notice of.</p>
               <p>Thus <hi>Dionyſius,</hi> when Two young Men were brought before him, (who, in their Cups, had ſpoke many Treaſonable Words a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him,<note place="margin">Apothegm. Fol. <hi>364.</hi>
                  </note> as being a Tyrant, and an unjuſt Oppreſſour,) he invited them both to Supper, and obſerving one of them to be a natural Drunkard, and idle Talker, him he diſmiſſed, and ſent him about his Buſineſs, as one not worth minding, being only made foul mouth'd by Drunkning: But the other, whom he obſerved very cautious both in drinking and ſpeaking, he put to Death, reputing him his Enemy, becauſe he ſpoke deliberately.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE XVII.</hi> How to find out the Secrets of Sober Men.</head>
               <p>YOU may find out the Inclinations and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets of a Sober Perſon, by moving his Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:65868:32"/>and ſetting his Mind on edge, and by obſtinate and reproachful Controverſies, by which being once moved (in Paſſion, and of his own accord) he will paſs a true Sentence, and diſcover his Inclination. Or you may try what is, or hath been the Inclination of one, when at School, whether Sober, Patient, Wrathful, Contentious, or given to Lying and Swearing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE XVIII.</hi> How One may know what Reputation he is of, and what is his Character in the Eyes of others.</head>
               <p>HE that would know his own Character, and the Opinion which others have of him, muſt praiſe or diſpraiſe, before ingenious Men, another like himſelf, both in Life and Manners; or praiſe or diſpraiſe him, who is (for the moſt part) given to Qualities quite contrary to his own. And, by this, he may know that they who praiſe one of his Life and Manners, and diſpraiſe one different in Life and Manners, do certainly commend and approve of him; and that they who diſpraiſe one like
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:65868:33"/>him, and praiſe one who is not like him, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not have any good eſteem, or think well of him.</p>
               <p>Thus <hi>Nero</hi> ſometimes praiſed <hi>Caligula,</hi> (whom he made the pattern of his Life,) and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times greatly diſcommended him, thereby to know what repute he himſelf had with others,<note place="margin">Seneca.</note> and in whom he ſhould put truſt. And, at laſt, finding what he ſought for, he put to Death all thoſe, who ſpoke reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully of him. But in ſuch as ſpoke to his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation, he put great Confidence, and made them his neareſt, deareſt, and moſt intimate Friends.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE XIX.</hi> How one may find out the Judgment of others, in a Caſe that concerns him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</head>
               <p>YOU ſhall know another's Judgment of your own Actions, or of your Friends, or of your Enemies, after this manner, propoſe to one, an Act of the ſame Nature, with your own, without mentioning the Actor, and then ask what the Perſon who hath done ſuch things
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:65868:33"/>deſerveth, whether praiſe or diſpraiſe, reward or puniſhment. Then, after you have heard his Sentence, ſhew the Caſes to be of one Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and Likeneſs; and the Author of the one to deſerve as much as the other. This is the ſureſt way; for on what a Man is Ignorant, and knoweth of no Relation to, he impartially paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth Sentence, freely and without fear. But, in things known, love or hatred blindeth the Eye of Reaſon, and oft times turneth the Scales of Juſtice to a partial Sentence: Tho it be juſt that every Perſon judge ſo of themſelves and Friends, as they judge of others in the ſame Caſes, and under the ſame Circumſtances.</p>
               <p>Thus <hi>Charles</hi> King of <hi>France,</hi> denounc'd War againſt <hi>Robert</hi> Duke of <hi>Aquitain,</hi> whom he overthrew, the Duke himſelf dying in the Battle,<note place="margin">Annot. Gal.</note> which ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and overthrow, <hi>Robert</hi> Earl of <hi>Vermandy,</hi> Nephew to the Duke of <hi>Aquitain,</hi> took ſo ill, that he laid Snares, and ſtill waited for an op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to be revenged on the King of <hi>France;</hi> therefore invited him, under pretence of Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, to <hi>Perona,</hi> to a yearly Feaſt: Whether the King, with a few of the <hi>French</hi> Nobility, without any Suſpition, willingly came. But, after Dinner, Earl <hi>Robert</hi> was pleaſed to ſeize them all, and keep them Priſoners in the Caſtle: But, after a whiles Impriſonment, he took an Oath of the Nobility, that they ſhould never
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:65868:34"/>riſe in Arms, or act any thing againſt him, and ſo diſmiſſed them. But ſtill detained the King, who after Two Years, died in Priſon. <hi>Lewis</hi> III. the Son of <hi>Charles,</hi> durſt not at firſt, when he came to the Crown, bring <hi>Robert</hi> in Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or reward him for ſerving his Father ſo; he having ſo many Favourites, Friends, and Relations in the Kingdom. But having invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a great many of the Princes, and Nobility of <hi>France,</hi> to a ſumptuous Banquet; and with the reſt, Earl <hi>Robert,</hi> a counterfeit Meſſenger, whilſt they were merry, made as if be had came from <hi>England,</hi> and delivered ſeveral Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to King <hi>Lewis,</hi> which he gave the Chancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour to Read. After the Reading of the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, he ſmiled, and with a ſhrill Voice, ſaid; <hi>This Letter makes the common report good,</hi> viz. <hi>That</hi> Engliſh-Men <hi>are no Politicians: For my Couſin Writes to me from</hi> England, <hi>That a Vaſſal there, an ill bred Countrey Fellow, invited his Lord to Supper, and after he had compelled him to ſtay all Night, ſtrangled him in his Bed.</hi> Then deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to know the Judgment of the Princes and Noblemen, there preſent, and what puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that Raſcal deſerved; earneſtly requeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that they might freely paſs a true Sentence, and ſpeak (as really) as they thought. When; with all the reſt, the Earl of <hi>Vermandy,</hi> ſaid, <hi>He deſerved to be put to Death.</hi> The King took up the Diſcourſe, and ſaid; <hi>Earl from your own
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:65868:34"/>Mouth I condemn you, as guilty of a Death-deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Crime;</hi> and immediately, commanded him to be ſtrangled. Thus, Earl <hi>Robert</hi> paſſed Sentence on himſelf, and received, for reward, the Parellel-Effect of his own Treachery.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE XX.</hi> How to know whether a ſuſpected Perſon be Guilty or not.</head>
               <p>YOU ſhall know if a ſuſpected Perſon be Guilty or not, if a firſt you accuſe him with falſe and fictitious Crimes; then with that which you ſuſpect him guilty of; and in the conteſt, in defending and proving, from his careleſs or careful behaviour, it may be known whether he be clear or guilty. For he ſligheth thoſe things whereof he is not guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and denyeth them after a careleſs underva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luing manner. But of thoſe things whereof he is guilty, he ſtriveth to clear himſelf ſeriouſly, and with great care. For a good Conſcience ſcorneth a falſe Accuſation, knowing it's own Innocence. But a true Accuſation moves the Paſſions, and Clogs the Conſcience with it's own guilt. Hence may be obſerved that an Accuſation is like the objects of our Senſes;
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:65868:35"/>for as a real preſent Object moveth that Facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, which naturally layeth hold on it, and whoſe proper Object it is: As Colour moveth the Sight, found the Hearing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> So likewiſe, a real Crime and Accuſation moveth the accuſed to a ſerious Vindication, whilſt he is not concerned at a falſe and fictitious Forgery. Moreover, ſound Sleep, a compoſed Mind, and a careleſs behaviour are great preſumptions of Innocence.</p>
               <p>Thus <hi>Titus Clodius,</hi> when he went to Bed in the ſame Chamber with his two Sons, was found next Morning Strangled: Whilſt no Perſon,<note place="margin">Cic. pro Sext. Roſc Amer. et val. Max <hi>8, 1.</hi>
                  </note> that could be ſuſpected, could be found. His Sons (who were of Age) decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that they knew nothing of it; nor could Conjecture who had committed the Murder. Yet the two young Men were both brought in Queſtion, for their Fathers Death. The thing being ſo ſtrange, unlikely, and incredible, that any ſhould enter the Chamber, whilſt the two Sons were preſent, to diſern the leaſt Motion<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and defend their Father. But when it was made known to the Judges, that they were found Sleeping in the Chamber with the Doo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> open; they were acquited, and cleared from all Suſpicion; which was the only ground o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> their being brought to Tryal. For it was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver known, that one after he had poluted him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:65868:35"/>by the Violation of all the Laws of God, Men, and Nature, could preſently Sleep, and take his quiet Reſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE XXI.</hi> How to know Secrets from Nature and Cuſtome.</head>
               <p>THE Preſumption is Great and Rational, which is taken from Cuſtom and Nature. From Nature, <hi>Soloman</hi> found out the right Mother of a Child; when two Harlots ſtrove for it, as we may read, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 3. <hi>Joſeph. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>Chap.</hi> 2.</p>
               <p>From Cuſtom <hi>Galba</hi> (as <hi>Suetonius</hi> relates) found out who was the right owner of a Horſe, when, in Tryal of Law, it could not be deci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded. For the foreſaid <hi>Galba</hi> cauſed the Horſe to be led blind-fold to the Well, where he uſed to drink; and then, being ſet at Liberty, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the Horſe to be delivered to him, whoſe Stable he went to.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="part">
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:65868:36"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE XXII.</hi> How to prevent and eſcape hidden Snares.</head>
               <p>IF you be informed that private Miſchiefs, and ſecret Snares, are laid out for you, (which, openly, and by out ward force, you cannot repel;) you muſt, by all means, carry your ſelf, as if you knew nothing of them; for, in ſo doing, you will have the better opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and may, with the greater eaſe, prevent and fruſtrate them. But if your Adverſaries ſuſpect, or find out an Informér, they will ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten their Enterprizes, and run all hazards, to the utmoſt. Thus <hi>Hanno,</hi> a <hi>Carthaginian King,</hi> had deſigned, at his Daughter's Marriage, to poiſon or kill all the <hi>Senate,</hi> that without Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, he might reign abſolutely. Whereof the <hi>Senate</hi> being, privately informed, they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed their Knowledge of ſo pernitious a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign. But, before the Marriage came, they made a Law, prohibiting all ſumptuous Feaſts, and that many ſhould not be invited to a Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet, as if they had only ſtruck at Vice and Riot; whilſt, in the mean time, they ſaved the <hi>Commonwealth</hi> by their Law.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="part">
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:65868:36"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE XXIII.</hi> How to Anſwer difficult and dubious Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions, without Danger.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>HE that would ſhun dangerous Anſwers, and decline a Neceſſity of anſwering a difficult Queſtion, which (however warily it be anſwered) putteth the Anſwerer to a loſs, muſt be cautious not to anſwer directly, but prove it difficult and ſlippery, by ſome Parel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lel; whereby you may come off, with credit, and without loſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thus a certain</hi> Jew, <hi>was asked by the</hi> Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour <hi>of the</hi> Turks, <hi>what Religion was beſt, whether that of the</hi> Jews, <hi>the</hi> Chriſtians, <hi>or the</hi> Mahumetans. <hi>The</hi> Jew <hi>ſuſpecting that he had propoſed the Queſtion to enſnare him, to ſpeak Treaſon, in condemning the</hi> Emperour<hi>'s Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; to find an Occaſion to forfeit and take away his Eſtate; and, on the other part, think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the</hi> Emperour <hi>would repute him a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling Hypocrite, and Sycophant, if he ſhould condemn his own Religion, anſwered thus,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A Man, on his Death Bead, gave a Ring to his only Son, whom he intirely loved; on that Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, that his Son would leave it to his Son, whom
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:65868:37"/>he moſt loved; who ſhould likewiſe leave it to his Son; that, for many Generations, it might ſo paſs (if poſſible) to the end of the World, or as long as his Race continued. Now, it fell out that one of the Line had Three Sons, whom he equally lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and the ſame Three Brothers did mutually love one another, without difference. Therefore, thought, that to give the Ring to One, was a ſlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Reſt, and might prove a means to raiſe hatred among the Brethren. But, on ſecond Thoughts, gave the Ring to a Gold-Smith, to make Two Rings exactly like it, ſo that one might not be known from the other. And then, on his Death-Bed, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led for his Sons, ſeverally, and gave every one of them a Ring, as the Hereditary Memorial he had got from his Father, which the Father's deareſt Son was to inherit; deſiring every one to be ſilent, and conceal from his Brothers the receiving of the Ring. Every one promiſed Secrecy, and all, mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually, loved one another, as before: till, after the Father's Death, there fell out a Conteſt, who was the Father's Deareſt Son. Then (that every one might prove himſelf to be him) they brought out the Rings, which they had long concealed, every one thinking that he and none other had had the Ring. But, when the Rings were brought, they were ſo like one another that the Hereditary could not be known, and the Conteſt is not decided till this Day; And what are the Three Religions but theſe three Rings?</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:65868:37"/>
                  <hi>By which</hi> Simile, <hi>the</hi> Jew <hi>ſhunned the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous Anſwer to the</hi> Emperour<hi>'s</hi> Queſtion, and came off without loſs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE XXIV.</hi> How to ſhun an offenſive Anſwer or Sentence.</head>
               <p>WHEN a direct and downright <hi>Anſwer</hi> would give Offence, (for <hi>veritas odium parit,</hi>) Anſwer by ſome ſimilitude that is witty and pleaſing; or that the Queſtion is hard, and far exceedeth your mean Apprehenſion; and that it would take the Deciſion of a greater Wit, as never well yet decided; and that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you are not bound to do that which lieth not in your Power. But if there be ſome emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent danger at hand, and the caſe cannot be brought to Tryal without both danger and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, then ſome other more memorable Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize, of greater Importance, muſt be caſt in, to ſtop the Courſe and Current of the other.</p>
               <p>Thus <hi>L. Scylla,</hi> when the Legions, or Trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n'd Bands, of <hi>Rome,</hi> were up in Arms, and ſet on edge, by their own Phancies, and could not be brought to Tryal, for their Sedition, without great Offence to the Citizens, and loſs to the <hi>Commonwealth;</hi> made up the Matter with
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:65868:38"/>his witty Advice: Fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, by the ſound of Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet, and beat of Drum, he ſurpriz'd them, with the Alarm of the Enemy's Approach; and ſo the Sedition was at an end, all joining to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether to oppoſe the common Enemy.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE XXV.</hi> How to ſhun a difficult Sentence.</head>
               <p>A Hard Queſtion, which hath not been for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly decided, ſhould be given over; and a doubtful Cauſe delayed to a longer time; rather, than that a Sentence ſhould be paſt, which would repeal and deſtroy it ſelf.</p>
               <p>Thus, <hi>Corax,</hi> the Firſt, after the Death of <hi>Hieron,</hi> taught the <hi>Syracuſians,</hi> the Art of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuading, and <hi>Rhetorick,</hi> for reward: with whom <hi>Tyſius</hi> made the Agreement, That he ſhould not give him his reward, till he had taught him his Art; and then, when he had learn'd it, he might demand his Money. <hi>Corax,</hi> after a competent time, thinking he had taught <hi>Tyſius</hi> ſufficiently, demanded his Mony. But, his Scholar denying, to Law they went. And, when the Cauſe came to Tryal, <hi>Tyſius</hi> defend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed himſelf by this <hi>Dilemma.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:65868:38"/>
                  <hi>If I can perſuade the Judges that I owe you no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, they will abſolve me, and ſo am bound to pay you nothing, according to the Sentence of the Judges. And if I can not perſuade them, then am I leſs bound to pay you any thing, becauſe you have not taught me the Art of perſuading. Thus, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I perſuade the Judges or not, I will pay you nothing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But</hi> Corax, retorting his Arguments back on himſelf, ſaith, <hi>If you perſuade the Judges, you are bound to pay me, becauſe I have perfectly taught you the Art of perſuading. But if you cannot perſuade them that you owe me nothing, then I ſhall be pay'd, according to the Sentence of the Judges.</hi> But the Judges, fearing to involve themſelves in ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricate a Caſe, and Cauſe, very wiſely, decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned their paſſing Sentence; and diſmiſſed them with this Check, <hi>Mali Corvi, Malum Ovum,</hi> ſuch Maſter, ſuch Scholar; Rogues both, get you gone.</p>
               <p>There are, likewiſe, many Cauſes brought to a Tryal of Law, whom the <hi>Statute</hi> cannot reach, without granting ſome wicked Deſign; becauſe of ſome particular Circumſtances, which a General Act, Statute, or Decree cannot reach, be it never ſo Juſt and Rational. Therefore the Judge, out of his own Wit, Judgment, and Diſcretion, ought to find out ſome way to paſs Sentence, according to the Statute of the Law, which, if it were put in Execution, would
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:65868:39"/>bring the Executer under great Danger. As for Example.</p>
               <p>There were at <hi>Venus</hi> two rich Men, one <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonio</hi> a Chriſtian and Merchant; and another <hi>Ben-Ezra</hi> a Jew and great Uſerer, whom <hi>Anto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nio,</hi> in all Companies, did defame as a baſe, bad, and Covetous Man: But it fell out that <hi>Antonio</hi> (being put to a ſtrait) was forced to go to <hi>Ben-Ezra,</hi> to borrow a certain Sum of Mony. The <hi>Jew</hi> admir'd that he would have come to him, (upon ſuch an account,) whom he had ſo much defamed, and abuſed. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, he agreed to lend him the Money, on Condition, that if he brought it again to him, on, or before the Day appointed, <hi>Ben-Ezra</hi> was to give it to him freely; but if not, he was to pay him with a pound of his Fleſh. <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonio</hi> being put to it for Money, and not queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oning the Payment, before the Day appointed, took it on theſe Terms; but things falling out contrary to his Expectation; and having loſt ſeveral Ships at Sea, could not return the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, till two Days after the time; and then <hi>Ben-Ezra</hi> would not take it; but a pound of his Fleſh, according to the Agreement. Therefore, to Law they went, and, at Tryal, according to the Statute, <hi>Antonio</hi> was caſt; the Caſe being a clear Contract, Sealed, and with Witneſs; which the Law of <hi>Venus</hi> could neither ſhun nor ſlight. <hi>Ben-Ezra,</hi> willing to be revenged on
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:65868:39"/>
                  <hi>Antonio</hi> was glad of the Judges Determination, ſo much, that (when the Judg ſaid, Ben-Ezra <hi>may chuſe out of what place ſoever of his Body he pleaſeth, to take his pound of Fleſh, ſince no place was determined</hi>) he cried out, <hi>a Daniel, a Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel,</hi> meaning a juſt Judge. <hi>Antonio</hi> (know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the irreconcilable Revenge, and inſatiable Thirſt, which <hi>Ben-Ezra</hi> had againſt his Perſon, and ſucking his Blood) reputed himſelf a dead Man; and after ſeveral Sighs, and ſad dejected Looks on the Judge, which he preſented as Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions, for a favourable Sentence, (which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, the Judge could not paſs, contrary to the Statute of the Law,) was taken from the Bar, to pay the <hi>Jew</hi> a pound of his Fleſh. But, as they were a going, the Judge called to the <hi>Jew;</hi> Ben-Ezra, <hi>you term me a juſt Judge, and I ſhould be ſorry if you had Reaſon to think me otherways; but I perceive that your Action againſt</hi> Antonio <hi>is but to be revenged on his Perſon, and that you are abſolutely deſtitute of all Mercy. Therefore, aſſure your ſelf, that if in taking your pound of Fleſh, you ſhed one drop of his Blood, you ſhall ſatisfie for it, according to the Law of</hi> Venus; <hi>for I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be leſs juſt to</hi> Antonio, <hi>than to</hi> Ben-Ezra. This ſo ſtupified the Blood-thirſty <hi>Jew,</hi> that he was glad to diſmiſs <hi>Antonio,</hi> without paying of his Money.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="part">
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:65868:40"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE XXVI.</hi> How to ſpeak One's Mind freely, without danger.</head>
               <p>YOU may, without fear, ſpeak what in it ſelf is dangerous, if you aſſume, and act under the Perſon of another, whoſe Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge it is to ſpeak freely, without Danger of Puniſhment.</p>
               <p>Thus, <hi>Labenius,</hi> an Old Knight, and <hi>Sena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> (when, againſt the Dignity of his Place and Perſon, he was compelled by <hi>Julius Caeſar,</hi> to dance on the Theater,<note place="margin">Apoth. Fol. <hi>517.</hi>
                  </note> and Act with common Jeſters, thoſe witty Plays, which for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly he had Written) revenged himſelf on <hi>Caeſar.</hi> He took upon him to Act the part of <hi>Syrus,</hi> the Slave; and as he had been beat, by his Maſter, fled grumbling, and cried out, we <hi>Romans</hi> have loſt our Liberty, whereby he plainly taxed <hi>Caeſar</hi> for his Tiranny; and then, a little after, added, <hi>He muſt needs fear many, whom many fear.</hi> On the hearing of which, the whole People began to ſtare upon <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and whiſper concerning him; knowing that <hi>Labenius</hi> had ſpoke theſe Words to check his Tiranny.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="part">
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:65868:40"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE XXVII.</hi> How to ſpeak what you pleaſe, without any danger.</head>
               <p>ONE may be driven to ſpeak that which, conveniently, he cannot; becauſe they would be ill taken, as coming from his Mouth. For which Cauſe, the Figure, in Rhetorick, <hi>Proſopoſoeia</hi> (by which an Orator may ſpeak what he pleaſeth, by aſcribing it to another Perſon) was invented. So likewiſe, he that cannot, without danger, give a wholſome Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel, concerning Publick Affairs, as being pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited to be ſpoke of, muſt feign himſelf to be out of his Wits; and then without fear or danger, may proclaim his Councel; notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, of the contrary Decree.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Quin. lib.</hi> 9.2.</note>
               </p>
               <p>This was <hi>Solon</hi>'s Courſe, when there had been ſo long a Continuation of War, and ſuch an Univerſal Slaughter, betwixt the <hi>Athenians,</hi> and the <hi>Magareans,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Juſt. Lib. <hi>2.</hi> Laert. lib. <hi>1.</hi> in vita Solon.</note> upon the account of his Native Countrey <hi>Salamis,</hi> that, on both ſides, they were almoſt quite deſtroyed; and the <hi>Atheni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> had decreed, that the mentioning a Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the Iſle <hi>Salamis,</hi> ſhould, ever after, be taken as a Capital Crime. <hi>Solon,</hi> knowing
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:65868:41"/>that his Silence could do no Kindneſs to the Commonwealth, and his giving Councel might prove dangerous, he, ſuddainly, feigned him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf mad; under which Veil, he could not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpeak, but act what he pleaſed, for the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of the Common-wealth; notwithſtanding, of the <hi>Athenian</hi> Decree. Then, having diſgui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed himſelf, in the habit of a Fool, ran out to the Market-Place; and when the People had gathered about him, (the better to cover his counterfeit Madneſs,) in a unuſual ſtile of Rhime, he began to perſuade the People, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out delay, to denounce War againſt the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gareans,</hi> and the Iſle of <hi>Salamis,</hi> in a ſhort time would be theirs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE XXVIII.</hi> How to ſhun the Reproach of an unhappy Adventure.</head>
               <p>LEST any blame you, for a raſh underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, which proveth bad in the event; you muſt carry it, as if the reſult were uncertain, and as it were not known, what might be the event; and take his Advice, whoſe Buſineſs it is, what is beſt to be done; then, when you both agree
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:65868:41"/>in one Judgment, and his Councel prove the ſame with yours, ſhew him the unhappy event; and, by this means, you ſhall ſhun his Reproach, and Reproof: For, agreeing to the ſame Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, he cannot, in Reaſon, condemn the event of his own Advice.</p>
               <p>Thus, when <hi>Hannibal,</hi> the Elder, the Son of <hi>Guiſcon,</hi> was beat in the Firſt Sea Fight, of the <hi>Punick War,</hi> he ſent, with all ſpeed, a Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger to <hi>Carthage;</hi> to know whether or not he ſhould Fight the <hi>Romans,</hi> on the firſt opportunity.<note place="margin">Val. Max. <hi>7.3.</hi>
                  </note> To whom all the People, with one Univerſal Voice and Conſent, anſwered; <hi>Fight them without de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay, and let nothing hinder.</hi> Then the Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger added, <hi>We have engaged, and are beat.</hi> Then they were all ſilent, who had, otherways (if it had not been for their own Councel) dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Hannibal,</hi> and his Fight too; and might, perhaps, crucified himſelf; which was then the Cuſtom of the <hi>Carthaginians.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="part">
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:65868:42"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE XXIX.</hi> How to ſpeak that, which, in it ſelf, is dangerous, without hurt.</head>
               <p>WOrds which one <hi>will</hi> ſpeak, and are apt to bring both hatred and danger to the Speaker, ought not to be ſpoke openly; but ſignified, obſcurely, by ſome witty knack; and this in <hi>Rhetorick,</hi> is termed <hi>Innuitio;</hi> by which <hi>Figure,</hi> one may, covertly, make that known, which he can not conveniently ſpeak openly; by bringing in an <hi>Antecedent,</hi> from whence, of neceſſity, and readily, the Hearer may know his hateful and paſſionate meaning.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Demoniades Lacon,</hi> uſed this <hi>Figure</hi> in his Vindictive Paſſion. For when he had loſt his Slippers, he earneſtly wiſh'd, that they might fit the Feet of him that ſtole them. Now he ſeemed to pray a very ſober and lawful Prayer, whilſt, indeed, his Prayer was a wicked Impre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation; for he wiſhed a Miſchief upon the Thief, <hi>viz.</hi> That his Feet might turn a wry, and that he might have crooked Club Feet, ſuch as <hi>Demoniades</hi> himſelf had. For he that wiſheth that the Slippers might fit the Thief's
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:65868:42"/>Feet, concealeth the bad Conſequence, <hi>viz.</hi> That the Thief's Feet might be ſet a wry, to fit the crooked Club Pattons.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE XXX.</hi> How to ſhun that which is hateful to One, by a Jeſt.</head>
               <p>IF Neceſſity force you to ſpeak, that which, otherways, you would not; ſpeak it by way of Jeſt, as if you did it not Seriouſly, and with Deliberation.</p>
               <p>Thus, a certain married Woman, which had made her Husband a Cuckold, went to confeſs her Sins to a <hi>Prieſt.</hi> But, before he would give her a full Pardon, he bound her to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge her overſight to her Husband; and that her Young Son was none of his. The Adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſs was hardly put to it, not knowing how to keep her Credit, her Husband's Fovour, and diſcharge her Conſcience towards the Prieſt. But, taking advice of a Neighbour, ſhe put on a Begger's Habit, and (as another Perſon) told her young Son; (as it had been to fright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en him;) whilſt he was crying, and making a noiſe, <hi>Get you gone ſqualing Rogue,</hi> and then tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:65868:43"/>her Face to her Husband, (as it had been to make the Boy hold his Peace,) ſaid; <hi>You're not the Father of this bawling Boy.</hi> And, by this means, ſhe thought ſhe had confeſſed her ſelf an Adultereſs to her Husband, which ſhe had promiſed to do to her Father Confeſſor. But this Jeſt was an impious and wicked cheat, and a <hi>Hocus Pocus</hi> prank of Popery.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE XXXI.</hi> How to Reveal a Secret, without giving Offence to him that did reveal it.</head>
               <p>IF One tell you a Secret, which you willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly would reveal; you muſt ſeriouſly tell him that you knew it before, and that you came to the Knowledge thereof, by ſuch and ſuch Perſons, as he cannot conveniently enquire at; and ſo it would be reputed a piece of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent Nonſenſe, to urge you with an Oath or Promiſe of Secrecy; or to bind you to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal that, wherewith your preſent Informer hath nothing to do; nor are you any ways oblig'd to him, for telling you no more, than what you knew before.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:65868:43"/>Thus, When <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> was taken by the <hi>Venetians</hi> and <hi>French, Anno</hi> 1204. The <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarch</hi> there, was forced to condeſcend that there ſhould never afterwards be choſen any <hi>Patriarch, Arch-Biſhop,</hi> or <hi>Clergy-man</hi> whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever of St. <hi>Sophia</hi>'s <hi>Church,</hi> but a <hi>Venetian</hi> born; yet privately wrote to the <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Rome Innocent</hi> III.<note place="margin">Codr. Exact. Innocent <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> that the <hi>Venetians</hi> did encroach on the Liberties and Priviledges of the <hi>Roman See. Innocent</hi> (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he could not obey the <hi>Patriarch</hi>'s Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, in concealing what he was informed of) preſently wrote back to <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> that he had been, before he wrote to him, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed of the <hi>Venetians</hi> Inſolence, Thus, <hi>Moreover, Tho you have informed us, by your Letters, of ſeveral things, whereof you thought us ignorant, be aſſured that, before yours came to our hands, we had a clear and certain Information of the moſt part of what we have received of you.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE XXXII.</hi> How to reprove one without giving Offence.</head>
               <p>IF you would reprove anothers Vice, or would rather adviſe or admoniſh him not to fall into ſuch an Error; do it not directly, for,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:65868:44"/>in ſo doing, you would ſeem to accuſe him, as guilty of ſome act of Baſeneſs, and to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain evil thoughts of him, whereby you may give Offence, and, inſtead of mending one Errour make two. Therefore behave your ſelf as ignorant of his Faults, and as if you had not the leaſt ſuſpition of any ſuch thing; but, after an indirect manner, ſeign to reprove ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther before him, who hath committed, or is like to commit the ſame Error; then open to him how baſe and ſhameful a thing it is; and, if you can conveniently, perſwade your Friend (whom you would reprove but dare not) to check him upon that account, with ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proachful Name, agreeing to the nature of his Errour: And ſo, by this means, he himſelf may come to know, loath and leave of his Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, and be glad that he was not found guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of ſo horrible a Crime, nor was directly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved for his Fault.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE XXXIII.</hi> How to ſhun the Inconveniences of Jeers and Satyrs.</head>
               <p>YOU ſhall ſhun the venom of <hi>Scoffing</hi> and reproachful <hi>Satyrs,</hi> if you behave your
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:65868:44"/>ſelf as you did not mind them; and this is a ſure and Heroick rule, which no wiſe Man will diſcommend.</p>
               <p>This was the advice of <hi>Diogenes</hi> the <hi>Cynick,</hi> to a young Man who greatly complained that he was much troubled,<note place="margin">Laert Lib. <hi>6.</hi> in Decl.</note> at the Scof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fing and Satyrical Reflections of <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nys, Mimicks,</hi> and Stall-Jeſters, who could never forbear him in publick. You (ſays he) <hi>Shew your ſelf too much troubled at their Impertinencies:</hi> Meaning that there is no better way to ſtop the Mouths of ſuch Pedantick Idle Fops, than to ſlight their fooliſh Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, as not worth the taking Notice of. For by this means, you ſhew your ſelf unconcerned at their Scoffs, as if you neither valu'd them nor their foul Mouth'd Language either, which will appear by your not retorting ſuch Jeers at them, as they throw at you: Or, in taking no care to free your ſelf from the vain tattle of ſo impertinent Perſons. And this will gall and perplex the Satyriſts and Idle Perſons, more than if you ſhould make Orations, and Write Volums, in ſpite, againſt them.</p>
               <p>Thus, when two Learned Men did paſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately and ſharply Write one againſt another, the Firſt and Wiſer, to ſtop the Mouth of his Adverſary, did upbraid himſelf and his Tribe with all the Vices which are incident to Men, and all the Crimes that attend a debauch'd
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:65868:45"/>Life; gathering a cluſter of bitter Grapes, and bad Language from <hi>Plautus</hi> and other ſuch Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, which none but Scolds and Scoffers uſe: Whereby his Adverſary (having nothing to ſay againſt him, but what he himſelf had ſaid already) was vext and gall'd in his Mind, and with ſhame, put to ſilence as one ſlighted, and not worthy to be minded, or his Diſcourſe to be taken Notice of. Neither did any Perſon think the worſe of the other; For all his op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probrious Accuſations (whether true or falſe) coming from his own Mouth, they were belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by None, but he himſelf was reputed the Wiſer and Better Man.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ro</hi> bore nothing with greater Patience than baſe Language and Calumnies: Neither did he paſs any affront with leſs Puniſhment than ſpiteful Satyrs,<note place="margin">Sueton. in Neron. <hi>39.</hi>
                  </note> whether in Word, or Write; Verſe, or Proſe. For when any came to his hand, he neither ſearch'd after the Authors, nor Puniſht thoſe who were brought before him and found Guilty, with any great Puniſhment.</p>
               <p>Thus, if a vindictive cruel Tyrant (who fiſh'd in all opportunities, to Bathe himſelf in humane Blood, on the leaſt offence,) could paſs and ſlight Jeering, Scoffing, and ſpiteful Language, as not worth minding; how much more ought a Sober Patient Man, of a ſounder Principle, (who hath not half the Power of
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:65868:45"/>the Emperor <hi>Nero</hi>) ſlight the babling of idle Jeſters, and Satyrical Fools: Who are neither fit for any Buſineſs, nor worthy to be kept Company with.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE XXXIV.</hi> How to induce a Prince to hear one Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently.</head>
               <p>THE firſt and principal Means, whereby a Prince is induced to lend an attentive and patient Ear, and is made fit for your In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, is ſweet pleaſing Words, and Flattery. For moſt Princes being incident to this infirmity, that they are of Opinion, <hi>They are the only Men which are reputed Wiſe, and capable to Manage great Affairs, and give ſound Advice:</hi> Say what one will in their Commendation, they think it no more than what they Deſerve. Hence it follows, that tho' one procure that good E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents be eſteemed the Fruit of his good Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, or ſhould accompliſh by his Wit and Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, ſome worthy and memorable Act (which might do his Prince a great Favour) all the Applauſe, which by right is his, and which he ſhould in Juſtice reap, will be attributed, not ſo much to his Wisdom and Dilligence, as
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:65868:46"/>to good Fortune: Yet, by this means one may creep a little further in his <hi>Prince</hi>'s Favour, but no other ways than an Actor in a Play. For, he who aſcribeth the Victory to Fortune, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries away the Triumph without the hatred of him who is overcome: but he that attributeth it to his own ſtrength and skill, carrys away the Victory with Envy, Hatred, and Revenge.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="35" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE XXXV.</hi> How one ought to behave himſelf, and what courſe he ſhould take, when he is environ'd with Danger and Difficulties on all ſides.</head>
               <p>WHen one is driven to that Condition, that, whether he ſtrive or ſit ſtill, his loſs, danger, and current of affairs, are ſtill the ſame, he muſt move and beſtir himſelf in thoſe Courſes, which are moſt likely to make for his Buſineſs. For, when one concealeth the event of his Affairs, which he committed to bare Wiſhes, and a fretting Mind, his Condition is nothing made better, but rather worſe; the Cauſes and Accidents of the Danger ſtill remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; whilſt, otherways, he who boldly with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandeth
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:65868:46"/>difficulties, either findeth out a way how to eſcape Dangers, or (if he bend his Wits, and ſpend his Labour in vain) ſheweth himſelf to be one of a daring Spirit, and Couragious Mind; for it is oft times found true, that
<q>Audentes Fortuna juvat, timidoſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> repellit.</q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="36" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE XXXVI.</hi> How Princes may conceal their Hatred, and private Diſpleaſure.</head>
               <p>A Prince, that would conceal his private grudge and hatred, againſt another Prince, till the Provocations break out in open War, muſt (to render him ſecure, and void of all Suſpition) Accoaſt and Congratulate him, with Gifts, Legats, and Embaſſadors, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as on his coming to his Dignity, his Kingdom, Crown, Superiority, and Dominion; his Marriage, or Birth of an Heir. And, to Grace all, every thing muſt be done, and preſented with the moſt plauſible Signs of entire Favour, Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and Familiarity. Which will prove very profitable, in proſecuting the intended Deſign.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="37" type="part">
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:65868:47"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE XXXVII.</hi> How to Aſſwage the Inſolencies of a Sedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious City.</head>
               <p>SWelling <hi>Cities,</hi> whoſe Inhabitants are Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to the Inſolencies of Inſurrection and Sedition, when they are under a Kingly Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, are kept in order, no better way, than by ſetting a <hi>Senate</hi> over them; or commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Management of Affairs to one Man, choſen and appointed by the <hi>King.</hi> For the Government of a People, in reſpect of their Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, is better and more agreeable to the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrary Will and Pleaſure of a King, when it is committed to the Care and Fidelity of a few, than of many, whoſe Unconſtant and Ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Drifts, claſh oft times againſt another.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="38" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE XXXVIII.</hi> How to Abrogate Privileges.</head>
               <p>IT is a ſingular piece of Secret Policy, in a King, to connive, at firſt, with the Inſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:65868:47"/>and Seditions of a People, which can neither bear with abſolute Liberty, nor abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Servitude; and (when he can ſtop the Courſe of their Sedition, and bring them to Tryal,) to give way to the Current of their Crimes, Villanies and Out-rages; That, after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, he may have a ſufficient ground where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to deprive them of their Priviledges and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munities, which may be termed <hi>Briars in the ſide of the Government,</hi> and Thorns in the Eyes of the <hi>Prince.</hi> And, whereas, ſuch Seditious Subjects, (in uſing ſuch dangerous and hurtful means, to loſe their Liberties and Privileges) have forfeit all that is theirs; they ought to be handled like thoſe, who, being Conſcious to their own Crimes, deliver themſelves up Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners, to be Judged by a Councel of War.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="39" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE XXXIX.</hi> How a Prince may fruſtrate an Enemy, with whom he intendeth to Wage War.</head>
               <p>A Prince that intendeth to invade another's Territories, and denounce War againſt any King, Prince, People, or Commonwealth; muſt keep his Deſign cloſe, to prevent the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, and whiſpering of the Courtiers, (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:65868:48"/>ſome may be private Informers,) and ſeem to prize and glory in peace, as the greateſt bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing in the World. And, to fruſtrate his Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries Information, Prevention, or Prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, he muſt ſend Subtil and well Accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh'd Ambaſſadorus, in whom he can put Truſt, who may ſlily pump his Enemy's Projects, without diſcovering his own. And if there be ſent any Ambaſſadors from his Enemy (who, perhaps, may be Jealous of his Deſign, and would Antidote the poyſon of War,) they muſt be detained beyond the appointed time; and, at laſt, ſent away without any poſitive Anſwer; by telling them, that he will ſend their Maſter an Anſwer, very ſpeedily; which may be delayed till all things be compoſed and put in Order, for proſecuting the intended Deſign.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="40" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE XL.</hi> How a weak Kingdom, or Commonwealth, may be delivered from the Power of a potent Enemy.</head>
               <p>IT is convenient for a Prince and People, who are not able to engage an Enemy, in open
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:65868:48"/>War, to ingratiate themſelves in their Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary's Favour, by confirming a durable Peace; or, to take for their Protection, ſome King, Prince, or People, more powerful than them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; or by buying their Peace, tho at a dear Rate. But it ſhould be obſerved, that Kings and potent Princes do not, always, openly, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in Leagues, offenſive and defenſive, with inferiour Dukes and Commonwealths, but in a private Compact or Agreement; leſt the inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our States ſhould ſeem to aim at great things, and think themſelves as good as their Patrons. And it is likewiſe a ſure way, to ſave Ones Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritories from Invaſion, ſubtilly and cautiouſly, to raiſe Seditious Jealouſies, and Inſurrections, in the Bowels of that Kingdom or Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, which moſt you fear; for by that means there may be ſome thing to do at home. Or, if that cannot be done, it is needful to raiſe ſome quarrel, or ſtir up a Foreign Enemy, to engage with ſo troubleſome a Neighbour; with Aſſurance of Aſſiſtance, both in Men and Money.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="41" type="part">
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:65868:49"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE XLI.</hi> How to moleſt Neighbouring Nations.</head>
               <p>THE fitteſt way to raiſe Broils, inteſtine Wars, Seditions and Inſurrections, in the Bowels of your Enemies Country; is to allure and ſtir up ſome of the Off-ſpring of the Prince, to undergo ſome hard, dangerous, and Seditious Undertaking, in purſuit of ſome Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Right and Intereſt, which he may have, or ſeem to have to the Crown, Government, or any other Regal Prerogative; only loſt by the Power, Wrong and Injuſtice of Ambitious Uſurpers: For there is no fitter way to delude the minds of the unſtable People than this. Hence it is, that thoſe who have been deſirous of change of Government, have ſtill been ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecting againſt the preſent; pointing at ſome Branch of the Royal Family, whoſe Right, the Crown and Government might be, as they Fancy. There is no neceſſity, here, to bring Examples, for there is neither King nor Subject, Prince nor People, but have heard of, or ſeen ſuch Tranſactions and Undertakings, in their own Time.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="42" type="part">
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:65868:49"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE XLII.</hi> How to Suppreſs thoſe who are proud of their Honourable Titles and Dignities.</head>
               <p>THE ſureſt way to Suppreſs thoſe ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Spirits, who are proud of their honourable Titles and Dignities, is to make theſe great Titles (which they ſo eſteem and brag of) common; by conferring them on new Start-up rich Sparks, who can look as big as they; and ſo theſe Titles, which once were courted, as moſt Honourable, and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the great ones were ſo proud, will be ſlighted as an ordinary thing. As for Example, if there be any who looketh big, for the Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of Duke, Marqueſs, Earl, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Let the King take one of his Domeſtick Servants, and confer on him one of theſe high, vain-glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, airy Titles (which adds nothing to the Man's Accompliſhments) as the juſt Reward of his Deſervings and good Service. And, by making him, with ſeveral others, of the ſame order of Chivalry; the high Titles will not make ſo geat a luſtre, and the ſwelling Peer will lay by his big Looks.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="43" type="part">
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:65868:50"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE XLIII.</hi> How to keep under Men of Ambitious and Aſpiring Spirits.</head>
               <p>ONE whoſe Wealth doth encreaſe, and elevates his proud Mind above the Sphere of an ordinary Subject, ſhould be ſent in Embaſſies; and put upon expenſive Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, of Ambition, Honour, and Greatneſs. And thoſe who have the Applauſe, and look big in the Eyes of the People, ſhould be drawn over by fair Speeches, and a proſpect of greater Honour; to be their Princes's Favourit: that thereby the Subjects may owe the greater Allegiance and Loyalty to their Prince, for countenancing ſuch Men. Thoſe who have a great Name, and make a great Figure in the Government, ought to be put upon hard and difficult Exploits and Expeditions: that, when the reſult of their Undertakings doth not anſwer the Expectation of their Admirers, their Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deur and great Eſtimation may be leſſened; and that the People may not dote on the Parts and Accompliſhments of any Subject, above the Enduments of their Prince. They who, at Court, aſpire in Greatneſs, Preheminence, and
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:65868:50"/>Superiority, above the Sphere of an humble Subject and Servant, ſhould be ſent to ſome Foreign Country, where they cannot have op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to proſecute their ambitious De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns. He who hath the Applauſe of an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Soldier, and is ſuſpected as dangerous in ſo eminent an Employ, ſhould be ſent from the Army, under ſome pretence, to ſome other honourable Function at Court: but ſuch as is deſtitute of all opportunity of moleſting the State of Affairs, or doing his Prince any Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindneſs. But, in one Word, Men of unſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfy'd Minds, who are ſtill fiſhing after greater Preferment, ſhould be ſent to Foreign Nations; about ſome publick Affair, whereby they may gain Honour, but become no more powerful, to work their private and dangerous Deſigns, of Promotion and Dignity. If of neceſſity, great Truſt in publick Affairs, muſt be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to a vitious <hi>Perſon of Quality,</hi> joyn with him a Sober, Loyal, and witty Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junct, and his Vices may be reſtrained, and he himſelf prove a good States-man. But the beſt courſe that a Prince can take, in the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of State-Affairs, is to make all Places and Offices of Government Temporal; and <hi>Durante Regis Beneplacito:</hi> leſt by conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuing too long in one Office, any ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to repute his Office his Hereditary Right, and look upon himſelf as a petty Prince.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="44" type="part">
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:65868:51"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE XLIV.</hi> How to Suppreſs Seditious Soldiers.</head>
               <p>THERE is no better Antidote to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the Sedition of mutinous Soldiers, or a factious Army, than to diſperſe them to ſeveral Places; for it was never known that a great Army could lie idle, without miſchievous Plots, Inſolencies, ond Out-breakings. And, if an Army be ſuſpected to contrive private Conſpiracies, and villanous Acts of Miſchief, not yet Diſcovered, all means muſt be uſed to come to the Knowledge thereof. And when the Intrigue is found out, ſomething muſt be caſt in, to ſtop the current of their Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Councils, and Contrivances, till there be a full Diſcovery of the whole Matter; and things be put in a poſture of Defence and Safety, to repel the Force of their miſchie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous Deſigns. Then, when this is done, a ſeeming opportunity ſhould be given, that they may haſten to accompliſh their Projects: whilſt indeed, the opportunity is but a trap, all poſſibility of their performing their wicked Deſigns being prevented. But it is a good way to keep an Army from plotting Miſchief,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:65868:51"/>to mix together Soldiers of ſeveral Nations and different Manners and Languages; for hardly can ſuch agree in one Faction, or live in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord among themſelves; much leſs joyn with one conſent in a Body, againſt their Prince or Commanders.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="45" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE XLV.</hi> How to Suppreſs Civil Seditions and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>proars.</head>
               <p>A Seditious People may be induced to go to Colonies and Foreign Plantations, in expectation of great Eſtates, and Land for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. Where they can have no opportunity of Plotting and Contriving Miſchief and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracies, which were occaſioned by their Idleneſs and and want of Employment; but be driven to Till the Ground, and uſe their dilligence for a Livelihood.
<list>
                     <item>(2.) If their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolency be come to an open Out-breaking, the interpoſing of plauſible Men, who have the Favour of the People; and whom they take to be Friends, to whom they will lend a patient and attentive Ear, is a very effectual Remedy to tame the Fury of a diſtracted Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</item>
                     <item>
                        <pb n="86" facs="tcp:65868:52"/>(3.) It is likewiſe a ſure way for a good and wiſe Man, of great Power and Repute, to pretend to eſpouſe the Quarrel of the ſwelling Multitude, till the tide of their Madneſs be over; and, under colour, to become their Captain or Ring-leader, thereby to ſave the Government from Rapine, Burning, Slaughter, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Who, though perhaps, he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſtop the current of their malicious Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours; yet may he mitigate their Fury, till a ſurer. Remedy be taken.</item>
                     <item>(4.) For Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing publick Inſolencies, a Foreign Force of Soldiers muſt be uſed: for, being Strangers of an unknown Tongue, they cannot ſo eaſily ſide with the Seditious, as thoſe of their own Nation, who may be induced to joyn with their own Countrey-People, upon the account of Friendſhip and Self-intereſt; or at leaſt connive at their Inſolencies, Outrages, and Inſurrections, as being their Friends and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey-men.</item>
                     <item>(5.) If theſe Remedies do not effectuate, and the Inſurrection muſt be Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed by Force of Arms, the Magiſtrates muſt go and ſeverely puniſh the Ring-leaders and Promoters of the Inſolencies, according to the extremity of the Law. Yet the Vulgar are ſtill to be excuſed; becauſe indeliberately, and by the perſuaſion of their Superiors, they undertook ſo villanous an Enterprize.</item>
                     <item>(6.) Seditions and Inſurrections, raiſed by the
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:65868:52"/>Cruelty and Covetouſneſs of Courtiers, and Stateſmen, may be appeaſed, by giving up to Juſtice thoſe firſt Offenders, who did ſet the People on edge.</item>
                     <item>(7.) Then let the Prince paſs an <hi>Act of Grace,</hi> proclaiming his free Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, of all paſt Crimes, to all ſuch as will come in to their Prince, and acknowledge their Error; ſo full, that no Court nor Law can lay hold on them; by which Clemency, all (ſome for fear of Puniſhment, ſome for Shame and Contempt, being deſtitute of their Leaders and Commanders) will come in, and make an humble Submiſſion.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="46" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE XLVI.</hi> How to know whether an Informer ſpeaketh Truth, or not.</head>
               <p>WHen the State of Affairs is ſo dubious and ſuſpected, that private ſubtile Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers muſt be uſed (thereby to know the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Deſigns and Intrigues of plodding and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contented Brains) it will be neceſſary to have ſeveral Informers, who have no acquaintance one with another; and when they all agree in one thing, without contradicting one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, then it is credible that they ſpeak Truth.
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:65868:53"/>But if they gainſay and contradict one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, there is no credit to be given to what they ſpeak; but diligent ſearch muſt be made by others, that, without delay, the certain Knowledge may be found out.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="47" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE XLVII.</hi> How one ought to behave himſelf, when he receiveth an Injury from a Perſon of Quality, that is far above him.</head>
               <p>TO ſerve a Prince, is a very hard and bad Employment, unleſs the Servant can ſo bear with Injuries, as if he knew nothing of them. For it is a very fooliſh thing for a Man to let his Paſſion be ſeen, when there is no way to revenge or right himſelf. Therefore, I ſay, there is no other Remedy for Injuries, given by great Perſons, than to behave ſo, as if one had not received them. For, if once a Perſon of Quality underſtand that their private Arts and Pranks are found out, and that the Perſon, to whom they owe a Spite, knoweth that they hate him, they will, with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen Violence, proſecute their Revenge ſo furi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, that they would be aſhamed ſo to do, did
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:65868:53"/>they not perceive that their private Intentions and Secrets were found out. Therefore, when either bad Words, a Miſtake, or Fault, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priveth one of his Prince's Favour, he muſt conceal his Misfortune, that he may not ſeem guilty. And then, tho his offended Maſter tyrannize over him, by open Reproofs Checks, ſecret Jeers, and Scoffs, he ought to overcome his Maſters Anger (which will in time wear out) by his dilligence and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Obedience.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="48" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE XLVIII.</hi> How to ſhun the Envy of Courtiers.</head>
               <p>Nothing haſteneth the overthrow of one ready to fall, whether by his own or anothers Errour, than Envy or Emulation, the conſtant Concomitants of Vertue and good Enduments; and the Tormenters and Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derers of Greatneſs and Promotion: To which commonly are joyned, the Complaints and Murmurings of the People, which ſpiteful Men uſe, as Witneſſes and Evidences, to work their Revenge, and proſecute their pernicious De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns, againſt thoſe whom they have ſet up, as the marks of their. Fury and undeſerved
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:65868:54"/>Malice, which altogeth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, and ſtir u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Mind of a Prince (tho' otherways n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>er ſo effable and indulgent) no otherways than the ſtormy Wind toſſeth the foaming Billows of the raging Sea. Neither is there any way to eſcape this Evil, but by Innocence and Modeſty. I ſay <hi>Innocence,</hi> that he may do his Maſters Buſineſs carefully and with great honeſty, to his Maſters beſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage. I ſay <hi>Modeſty;</hi> for, as Envy is kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by Pride and Arrogance, ſo by a gentle Behaviour, Effability, and keeping a Houſe neither too Prodigal, nor any waies Baſe and Miſerable, it is leſſened, and at laſt quite ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſhed. Therefore let every Courtier and States-Man, quietly and carefully, look after his Buſineſs, without a great Retinue. Yea, if he be Wiſe, let him not in any waies be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to thoſe vain Glories, which do not demi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh, but augment the Envy of Ambitious Spirits; whoſe chief Eye-ſore is anothers Greatneſs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="49" type="part">
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:65868:54"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE XLIX.</hi> How One ought to behave himſelf with of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended Princes and Peers.</head>
               <p>IT is an excellent way to deal with offended Princes, not to provoke them by a ſlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and froward Indifferency, and unſeaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Contradictions; but to ſtrive, by an humble Submiſſion, to pacifie their violent Wrath, thereby to obtain a patient Hearing. Neither muſt this be done at firſt daſh, but at a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient time and opportunity. For when an abſolute Power overſwayeth a weak and infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour Perſon's Juſtice and Right, an obſtinate Reſiſtance marreth, but mendeth not the Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. And when the Perſon (in whoſe Hand the Power lyeth) is pacified, and pardoneth him who was miſrepreſented an Offender, he can eaſily, afterwards, be brought to a right Underſtanding, and be convinced of his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Miſtake, and have greater Reſpect for him, who did humbly ſubmit himſelf to his Clemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, though falſly accuſed. Thus a certain, ſober, and wiſe Perſon of Quality, being falſly accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by ſom envious Courtiers, finding them reſolute (at any rate) to confirm their falſe
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:65868:55"/>Accuſations, notwithſtanding of his Innocence, when his incenſed Prince inquired, <hi>What d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> you deſerve for ſo Villanous an Enterprize?</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, <hi>Death;</hi> humbly ſubmitting himſelf to his Prince's Mercy; by which ſober Anſwer, he obtained both his Prince's Pardon, and, in a while, greater Favour; when the <hi>Intrigue</hi> of the matter was found out, to the perpetual ſhame and contempt of his Accuſers. Though, otherways, had he ſtood obſtinate in his own Defence, he might have undergone the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt ſeverity of the Law.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="50" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE L.</hi> How to Suppreſs the Vices, and wrong Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences of Partial Judges.</head>
               <p>FIrſt of all, great Care muſt be taken that Courts and Judicatories be not proſtitute to a filthy Crew of perverted Judges, who paſs Sentence partially for Reward, or at the requeſt of ſome great Perſon, or for the Favour they bear to any Party; but that all ſuch Places be freely conferred on ſuch as are knowing, well-deſerving, good and honeſt Men. For what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever a Man buyeth, he looketh upon as hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Money, whereof he is free to make his beſt.
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:65868:55"/>And thus a Magiſtrate, who hath bought his Place, with freedom taketh a Bribe, which is the Original, out-moſt Extent, and <hi>non ultra</hi> of all Filthineſs and Knavery. Hence ariſe Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, Slaughters, Robberies, contempt of the Laws, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Every one confiding that all Crimes howſoever heinous, can be bought off for Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney. Therefore, it is needful that all Judges have their Sallaries appointed them from the publick; and that they themſelves be bound, under a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere penalty, to take no Money, directly or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>directly, upon the Account of their Offices. Moreover, none ought to be appointed a Judge in his own Native Country; neither will a wiſe Man deſire it: For, whether he be an Honeſt Man, or a Knave, it will ſtill be preſumed, that he will paſs many partial Sentences; upon the Account of his Friends, Kindred, and Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="51" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE LI.</hi> How to ſuppreſs Luxury.</head>
               <p>THough the violence of inveterate <hi>Luxury</hi> be ſuch, that it cannot be reſtrain'd by moderate Meaſures; yet the good Example of a ſober Prince may avail more than the fear of
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:65868:56"/>puniſhment, appointed by Law. And it is a good Remedy againſt this Evil, to impoſe, not only great penalties on the Offenders, but alſo Cuſtom and Taxes on thoſe Commodities which promote the Vice; far greater than on Corn, and other ſuch Commodities, which no Perſon can live without. Thus, ſome will not buy their mad Frolicks at ſo dear a rate; and though others ſtill continue in their <hi>Luxury,</hi> yet will it turn to the publick good, the King reaping the profit of their prodigality.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="52" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE LII.</hi> How to render populous Cities unfit for Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions and Inſurrections, without loſs or detriment.</head>
               <p>WHereas Merchandizing maketh gain the only Object of its Labour, it turneth Men to be of mean Spirits, and abſolutely averſe from the expence of War, and any thing of Trouble; and begetteth a natural and dull In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination to Peace. Whence, Cities become plenty in Handicrafts, and Men, in the exerciſe of Trading, can be eaſily kept in good Order, without inſolencies and out-breakings. And,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:65868:56"/>for the encouragement of ſuch, a well-ſettled Peace is very expedient: by which, the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple's love and reſpect, and their own unity and profit are more gained and preſerved, than by all the charming Allurements and fair Speeches, that either Prince or Magiſtrate can invent. For, there is nothing that gaineth more ground on the Peoples Affection, than a peaceable Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and giving them means and occaſion of gathering Wealth. And thus People being buſied about their Lawful Employments, they never mind the Revolutions of State-Affairs, ſo that they be not deprived of the ſweetneſs of their Gain, which they reap by their Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and Merchandizing.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="53" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE LIII.</hi> How to appeaſe an incenſed People.</head>
               <p>TUmults and Seditions, raiſed by the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolencies and Miſcarriages of States-Men and perverted Magiſtrates, can be compoſed no better way, than by giving up thoſe who were the firſt Offenders, and the Original Cauſe of thoſe Inſurrections, to Juſtice; as a Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, to ſuffer for the peace of the publick, and pacifie, by their Death, thoſe whom they had
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:65868:57"/>abuſed and provoked in their Life; and by ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting up others in their ſtead, who are well qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified, of a good Repute and Eſtimation, among the People. But ſeldom, or never, is the Prince blamed for any Errour in Government, but his Counſellors and Miniſters of State, and provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Subjects, eſpecially Citizens (like the Dog who biteth the Stone, not minding the Hand from whence it came) never conſider the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal of their Grievances; but blame thoſe who execute what they are bound to perform, by the command of their Superiours. And, in ſuch Caſes, this is the Courſe and Remedy which both good and bad Princes take. For, the good expiate, the imputed guilt of thoſe Offenders, (who have misbehaved themſelves, by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting Crimes ignorantly) by puting them to Death. And the bad impute their own Crimes to others, and charge them with that envy and bad Conſequences, which by right is their own.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="54" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE LIV.</hi> How to keep the Favour of new Subjects.</head>
               <p>THere is one good way to govern a Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, who have a hand in chuſing Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:65868:57"/>of Government, when the People enter Articles with a new Prince, lately come to the Crown, which is this; Let not the Prince al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter any thing of the antient Laws, Manners, and Statutes, that did formerly belong to the People; nor diminiſh the Goods of his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, by exceſſive Taxes, Cuſtoms, or Fines. But let all, or moſt things, continue in their former State. And, that the new Kingdom may ſtill keep it's old Face of Affairs; Let all Magiſtrates, Officers, and others, in publick Employment, continue in their places, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out incroaching upon the People's Liberties, Immunities, and Priviledges. Yet let him know, by the by, that Ambitious, Head-ſtrong Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Policy, who commonly eye their own Intereſt, Greatneſs, and Preheminence, will be but little profitable to the ſtate of Affairs. For ſuch, are commonly blown up with a ſelf Opinion and Confidence, and do both by Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, Cuſtom, and Education, take a greater freedom in the Government than is fit, for a Subject to do.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="55" type="part">
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:65868:58"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE LV.</hi> Why Merchandizing is forbidden to the Nobility.</head>
               <p>OUR Anceſtors did debar Noble Men from Merchandizing, becauſe they thought it would wrong the common Intereſt of Towns and Cities; and that it would, by an illimited Liberty, hinder a more noble Commerce. Now it is believed, by all, that Merchandizing is below the Sphere and Grandeur of a Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. And this Opinion was, at firſt, by the Policy of Princes, infuſed in the Ears of the Nobility, and is now become a <hi>Maxime</hi> of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted Truth. For when Princes came to underſtand, that their greatneſs and ſecurity did lie in the Exerciſe of Arms, nor were ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant that if the Nobility ſhould once, take to Trading, and taſte of the Sweetneſs, which from thence redoundeth, they would lay by the Exerciſe of War, and follow the Exerciſe of Merchandizing. And, therefore, it was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to infuſe in them this Opinion, as a <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radox</hi> in Greatneſs and Honour, <hi>viz.</hi> that to buy and ſell, for the Deſire of Lucre, in a No<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bleman, was a baſe and ſcandalous thing; tho
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:65868:58"/>to other Perſons the Highway might be repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Honourable.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="56" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE LVI.</hi> Cancerning the Inſtruments of Power.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>CAligula Caeſar</hi> uſed to ſay that there were two things whereby Power was acquir'd, preſerved, and augmented; which were Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and ſtrength of Arms. For it is impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble that a Kingdom can continue ſafe, without ſometimes War, neither can Souldiers be kept without Money: when there is neither Peace without War, nor War without Money; nor can Money be had without Taxes; How then can Taxes be exacted, ſecurely, without hatred, heart-burning, and envy? But this we ſhall ſhow you hereafter.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="57" type="part">
               <pb n="100" facs="tcp:65868:59"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE LVII.</hi> How States-Men ought to behave them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, in aſſuming the Honour of Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morable Acts.</head>
               <p>THere is one great Evil among Princes, <hi>viz.</hi> that they cannot endure any to be reputed braver Men than themſelves. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they carry on Affairs, which are accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed with little labour and difficulty, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their own Meaſure and Contrivance. But the Management of all hard and more dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult Affairs they commit to the Conduct of others; who (tho by their own only Wit and Induſtry they accompliſh the Buſineſs) muſt lay down the Name and Honour, which is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly their own, at the Prince's Feet; who will think himſelf robb'd, if he carry not away the Garland, tho' he never knew how it was gain'd. Therefore, every one, who would be careful of his own ſecurity, ought to ſhun all hard and difficult Buſineſſes of great weight, as far as poſſibly he can: But if he cannot, let him be ſure to attribute the Name, Honour, and Conduct of all good ſucceſs, and well-managed
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:65868:59"/>Affairs, to the Wiſdom and Prudence of the Prince; and by this means he will ſhun his Princes Envy, and be in no danger of loſing his Favour.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="58" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE LVIII.</hi> How to appeaſe offended Princes.</head>
               <p>WHen a Nobleman findeth his Prince ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red up againſt him, by the Reports and Rumours of Envious Perſons, and that his fury is is like to tend to his Ruine and Diſgrace; firſt of all, his Wrath muſt be, timouſly, miti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated by the ſober advice of ſome great Favo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, in few Words; before he hazard to vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate himſelf in his Prince's Preſence: leſt, unawares, the Prince, by toſſing and torment<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, be provoked to greater fury. Neither doth a ſhew of ſtubborneſs and obſtinacy gain any great credit of Innocence; eſpecially, when one, with a brazen Face, carrieth himſelf too confidently in his Princes Preſence. For, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Eclipſed by the envy of his Enemies, he is not able, tho' Innocent, to deal with his Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces Fury; nor repreſent the Caſe, as it really is; nor remove the Cloud of bad Conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces which his Enemies Hatred hath produced.
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:65868:60"/>Therefore it is fit to give place both to the King's Wrath, and the falſe Reports, that both, in time, may wear out; and then when the Prince beholdeth the true face of Affairs, through the right end of the Glaſs, the matter without difficulty can be ſoon made up.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="59" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE LIX.</hi> How to impoſe Taxes, without the offence, and grumbling of the Subject.</head>
               <p>IF a Prince raiſe that, as a Tax, which is, in every place, cheap, and may be ſpared; and impoſe great Cuſtoms on ſuch Commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties as promote the Luxury of great and rich Perſons, and great Fines on all Riotous Livers, and ſuch as ſlight and deſpiſe his Acts and Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes of this Nature, he will gain ground up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the People's Affections, and raiſe Taxes without offence or grumbling. Moreover, it will be very acceptable, if he uſe any fiugal induſtry, upon his own account, and then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly lay out the gain'd Money for the benefit of the publick; with a ſhew of great Care and good Husbandry. For nothing pleaſeth Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects more, than when they ſee the King carefully look after the management of publick Affairs, and the Treaſury not waſted in Luxury.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="60" type="part">
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:65868:60"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE LX.</hi> How to collect Taxes without offending the Subject.</head>
               <p>THE Antients did not ſo much burden, with Taxes, the Borders and Limits of their Kingdoms, as thoſe places in the middle of their Territories, and nearer to their Courts and Perſons. And, to ſhun the offence and grumbling of Subjects, this advice muſt be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken: No publick Collectors muſt be choſen, who go in Perſon to private Houſes, who can be partial, or favourable upon the Account of Bribes, and ſelf Intereſt; but let, rather, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour Collectors be appointed, who can nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther add to, or diminiſh from their limited Power; to vex or oppreſs City or Country, under the veil of a pretended Power or Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilege. But it is abſolutely the ſureſt way, to chuſe for a Collector, one who is a free Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizen; or, if in the Country, one well ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted in the place, honeſt and of good re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, who may chuſe, out of his own Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, ſuch as can more kindly gain reſpect of the People, and without giving offence, may bring in the Taxes to the publick Treaſury.
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:65868:61"/>But if any Perſon refuſe payment, it is fitter, and will be better taken, that the Magiſtrate force them to a ſubmiſſive Obedience; than that a rude Collector ſhould uſe the illimited Rule of his own inſolency, who commonly uſeth no Diſcretion, and giveth no delay to the rigid Execution of his Power; but rather maketh his <hi>ſerving the Publick</hi> a Terrour and Bug-bear, to frighten the Subjects, and gather ſpoil to himſelf, from poor People, who are ſcarce able to pay the Taxes themſelves. But, laſt of all, the Charge of the Treaſury muſt be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to very honeſt Men, whoſe Lives and Converſations, are evidently known to be juſt and good; otherways, let the Taxes be never ſo great, the publick Treaſury will allways be empty.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="61" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE LXI.</hi> How Seditions are raiſed.</head>
               <p>INcendiaries uſe, by ſly, inſinuating Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels, to ſow the Seeds of Sedition, in going to the chief Towns and Cities, and under the veil of fair and lawful Pretences, adviſing the Magiſtrates, either privately, or at ſome pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Entertainment, when their Hearts are mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:65868:61"/>not to betray the publick Liberties, nor ſuffer their Country to be undone, with miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievous Deſigns; and that they ſhould remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, they live in a free Kingdom, and not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Slavery and Tyranny.</p>
               <p>Neither muſt they ſpeak any thing againſt the <hi>Prince,</hi> but ſo intricately, dubiouſly, and at ſo great a diſtance, that they may eaſily ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe it; and that none can lay hold upon it but rather, ſeemingly, cover his Imperfections, Whilſt, in the mean time, they diſcover and. whip his Nakedneſs. And if they find their Diſcourſe minded, and taken more than ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary notice of by ſome, they muſt make as if they would deal more familiarly and plainly with them, knowing their good, juſt and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Principle; and that they are good Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth's-Men. And then, with ſome ſighs openly, or whiſpering the chief Men in the Ear, they tell them of ſome Flaw or Imperfection in the Government, that they may ſeem, with a paſſionate and deeply concerned Geſture and Behaviour, to dread more than they dare diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover.</p>
               <p>Afterwards, you ſhall find a great many to look on thoſe as very honeſt Men, brave States Men, and the<note n="*" place="margin">The Caterpillars.</note> Pillars of their Country. And thus, at length with a concern ſomewhat ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowful, they ſpeak with greater freedom of
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:65868:62"/>their Prince; and Subjects begin to be weary of him, eſpecially when it is induſtriouſly ſpread about, among the Rabble, that the Natives are quite ſlighted, and that Foreigners and Strangers ſit, at the Helm of Affairs; who (tho they boaſt of their noble Race, and antient Families) once got their poor and miſerable Livings, by ſweeping of Ovens, or ſome ſuch ſordid Employment; yet now live high, ſuck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the very Blood of the Commonwealth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="62" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE LXII.</hi> How Rebels and Conſpirators are kept cloſe together, in one Body.</head>
               <p>AFter theſe Incendiaries have, by their Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievous Speeches, ſown the Seeds of Treaſon and Sedition, the Weeds of Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy and Rebellion begin to appear in open view, and they ſtill proceed further, laying hold on all Occaſions, uſing all means, and fiſhing for all opportunities, to enlarge the breach betwixt the King and his Subjects; and that all hope of Reconciliation may be caſt off, or as <hi>Tacitus</hi> ſaith, <hi>Quo minore ſpe Veniae creſcat ſceleris Vinculum,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">4 <hi>Hiſtory.</hi>
                  </note> &amp;c. whereby the Bond of their ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:65868:62"/>may increaſe, with leſs hope of Pardon, they uſe to oblige the furious Rabble with ſome notable out-rage; that if any hope of Pardon ſhould appear, they may take it for a Trap, wheedling Snare, or State Sugar-Plumb, which would but ſet their Teeth on edge; and ſo may not accept of it, tho' the Prince ſhould freely proffer it; the horrid guilt of their im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pardonable Crimes, being always before their Eyes.</p>
               <p>And it is to be obſerved, that Seditious Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, for accompliſhing their miſchievous Deſigns, take the opportunity of Marriages, Fairs, and publick <hi>Feſtivals;</hi> very fit times for their pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, and pernitious Projects.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="63" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE LXIII.</hi> The Arts and Tricks of Tirants,</head>
               <p>IT is one of the ſweeteſt Secrets in Tiranny, to bring over to Luxury, them whoſe fierce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs may be ſuſpected to reſiſt the Arbitrary Proceedings of Rulers.
<list>
                     <item>2. To forbid all Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els, without Exception.</item>
                     <item>3. To build Thea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tres in the chiefeſt Cities, in which Dancing, Playing, and fine Shows, which delude the Fancy, may be uſed; with the bewitching
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:65868:63"/>ſweetneſs whereof, the People being once ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, it will hinder them from returning to their former ſtoutneſs of reſiſting Tiranny.</item>
                  </list> And by Conſequence, they will be leſs able to do hurt either to Prince or Government, being they are become effeminate.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="64" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE LXIV.</hi> How to puniſh Seditious Peers.</head>
               <p>PUniſhment on great Perſons ought not to be inflicted publickly, but in private, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Old Rule of Policy; <hi>Magnos ſed pravos, vulgò tamen gratos, Ductores, in eo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem carcere, Cuſtodiri, puniri, ac Sepeliri debere,</hi> Great, but Evil Men, Ring-Leaders of Sediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, who have the Applauſe of the Rabble, ought to be kept, puniſh'd, and bury'd, in one and the ſame Priſon. For the puniſhing of the Vulgar térrifies the Peers, and daunteth their Boldneſs: But, by the Death of great Men, their Fury is ſet on edge, and their Hearts en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="65" type="part">
               <pb n="109" facs="tcp:65868:63"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE LXV.</hi> How to prevent Scarcety of Corn.</head>
               <p>TIlling of the Ground is the moſt uſeful and neceſſary of all Employments: for thereby are both Men and Beaſts ſuſtained; and without which, both, of neceſſity, muſt Periſh. Therefore, Surveyors and Overſeers, ought to be appointed, to ſee that every one, carefully look after the managing of his own Ground: Neither is it enough to ſtir Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandmen up with fair Words and ſweet Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſions; but, likewiſe, to aſſiſt them both with good Council, and ſupply them with what elſe they ſtand in need of; eſpecially, thoſe whoſe experience hath not made them perfect in the Art of Agriculture.</p>
               <p>Next, muſt all impediments be removed, which may prove ſtumbling Blocks in the way of good Husbandry; leſt Men giving themſelves to Hunting, Hawking, Drinking, Gameing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> They neglect their more ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Affairs, and make both themſelves and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Miſerable: Therefore Farmers and Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandmen muſt be prevented from trifling away their time, in going idle Journeys to Cities,
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:65868:64"/>from Suits of Laws, and be as great ſtrangers to the Bench and Lawyers, as to the Taverns and Muſick-houſes. Moreover, great Encour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agement and Priviledges ought to be given to ſuch as dig up barren Ground, which hath not been formerly Tilled: as that the Farmer ſhould pay little or nothing the firſt two years. But, what ever courſe be taken, unleſs the Civil Magiſtrate appoint publick Granaries and Treaſuries of Suſtentation (as Officers or War, do Magazines of Amunition) it will be impoſſible to prevent Scarcity, in Kingdom of Commonwealth: The unprovident Vulgar looking no further than the preſent time.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="66" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE LXVI.</hi> How to behave in time of Dearth.</head>
               <p>WHEN Dearth approaches, or is at hand, great care muſt be taken to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain a ſort of Fore-ſtallers, who taking the advantage of the times, make Corn dear, and Starve thoſe poor People who are deſtitute of Money, by their wicked Extortion and Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous Cheats: Whoſe Wickedneſs, if it cannot be quite ſuppreſſed, it may be at leaſt ſo far reſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:65868:64"/>that in the Corn Market, for a certain time, the poorer Citizens may have the priviledge to buy firſt.
<list>
                     <item>(2.) Searchers ought to be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, who in every corner, ſhall carefully obſerve thoſe Fore-ſtallers, to apprehend and carry them before the Magiſtrate, to be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed; for it is a Religious kind of Severity, which, by puniſhing a few wicked covetous Wretches, preſerveth the Lives of a great many.</item>
                     <item>(3.) In ſuch caſes, it is a point of Wiſdom, to raiſe high the Cuſtoms of ſuch Corn as is carried beyond Sea to Strangers; for when the great Cuſtoms deminiſh the Gain, the Merchant will certainly lay by his Trafique.</item>
                  </list>
But if thoſe Courſes cannot be taken, becauſe of the prevailing iniquity of the times; or, if taken, they anſwer not the intended end, in time of Famine, ſtronger Remedies muſt be taken.
<list>
                     <item>(1.) Overſeers muſt be appointed, to look after every thing belonging to the Buying and Selling of Corn.</item>
                     <item>(2.) It will be expedient to compute the number of Citizens, ſo that one may exactly know how much will ſuffice to ſuſtain the People; then a competent Meaſure muſt be allowed to every Perſon, as neceſſity requireth.</item>
                     <item>(3.) It will be expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to encourage Merchants and Seamen, with Rewards; as to allow the firſt Ship that go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth off, ſo much out off the Publick Stock; the next Ship ſomewhat leſs, and the third, as
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:65868:65"/>is convenient, with immunity of Cuſtoms, as long as the Famine laſts; either for Importa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Corn, or carrying, for a Seaſon, thoſe who can pay for their Paſſage; to ſome plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful Colony; or, at leaſt, keep themſelves in ſome other Country, till the Famine be over.</item>
                     <item>(4.) The chief point of Wiſdom conſiſts in a frugal Diſtribution of the Corn; neither is the People only to be regarded, but the Ground is alſo to be looked after; and Corn for Seed (leſt the Ground lie barren) ſhould be given to Husband-men, who will return it with Uſury.</item>
                     <item>(5.) It is a great point of Fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gality, to ſend ſturdy Beggers a packing, and not to ſuffer them in time of Famine, to live upon the Labours of induſtrious ſober Men.</item>
                     <item>(6.) It is proper, in time of Famine, to allow every Perſon the benefit of Fowling, and Fiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; which was in old times, by the Law of Nations, allowed to all without exception; tho great Men now limit both, by an uſurped Power and Prerogative.</item>
                     <item>(7.) Let Taverns, Publick Houſes, and Stews be ſhut up, and all high Feaſting and ſumptuous Marriages prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="67" type="part">
               <pb n="113" facs="tcp:65868:65"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE LXVII.</hi> How to preſerve Corn.</head>
               <p>CORN is better preſerv'd in the Ear, than when it is threſh'd out, and made clean from the Chaff and Straw; for, being deprived of its own natural Cover, it cannot be kept ſo ſound by any thing of Art.
<list>
                     <item>(2.) It is advantageous for the Husband-man; for the remembrance of the former Years plenty being ſtill before him, it ſtirreth him up to follow his Buſineſs chearfully, and without floth.</item>
                     <item>(3.) That Husband-men may not be able to caſt up, and make an eſtimate of what Corn they have, which might diſencourage them ſometimes, whilſt the Trouble and Expence exceedeth the Gain.</item>
                     <item>(4.) By this means Straw is preſerv'd for the Cattle, and other uſes.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="68" type="part">
               <pb n="114" facs="tcp:65868:66"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE LXVIII.</hi> How a Prince may beſt confer Honours and Places.</head>
               <p>THE importunity of thoſe, who court and ſeek Honours and Preferment, is one of the greateſt Inconveniences that mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſteth a Prince: For aſpiring Spirits think it an high injury, that any thing of that nature, ſhould be deny'd them. Therefore, with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petition of Merits, they make their humble Addreſſes, with importunate Petitions, which cannot well be contradicted. Thus, when the Prince obligeth one, by granting a Favour, he diſobligeth many by repulſes; neither is there any remedy for this Evil; the Prince not being able to oblige all, by granting their Requeſts. Whereupon, Cardinal <hi>Cajetan</hi> did, deſervedly ſay, that it was one of the principal Qualifications of a prudent Prince, <hi>To know how to deny a thing handſomly:</hi> maintaining, that he was not fit to govern, who knew not how and what to deny. But, in this caſe, it is the main and beſt caution, to prefer the ancienteſt of Competitors: for ballancing the Vertue and Merits of many, breeds Envy and Diſcord,
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:65868:66"/>but the priviledge of Age is without contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie.
<list>
                     <item>(2.) They who have come of a good Pedigree, and have deſerved well of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, have the next place: for up-ſtart Men, tho they ſhould excel thoſe, cannot take it ill, if ſuch be prefer'd to places of Truſt, if they be endued with any tollerable Qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</item>
                     <item>(3.) It is uſual with ſome, to joyn a Colleague and Partner to Officers of State; under ſome pretence, as Age, Weakneſs, and other Infirmities: Who, thereupon, being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinated to ſucceed the place, may exclude the hope and expectation of others.</item>
                     <item>(4.) Others, upon the ſame account, do advance to Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment, whom they think moſt fit for the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment, in the room of his Predeceſſor; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore too many Competitors have time to put in for it.</item>
                     <item>(5.) It is no ſmall point of prudence, before the Election, to ſend the more power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Competitor ſome where elſe.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="69" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE LXIX.</hi> How to keep what is Conquered by force of Arms.</head>
               <p>KIngdoms that are Conquer'd, by Force of Arms, are beſt kept by Juſtice in the King, and Moderation in the Magiſtrates, by impoſing
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:65868:67"/>and collecting Taxes deliberately and moderate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, by paying of Wages duly, and by uſing all means conducing to a well ſettled Peace. For whilſt Affairs are embroil'd at home, it is a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural conſequence, that there is little Reſpect or Eſtimation abroad. Therefore, thoſe King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms and Commonwealths, which maintain Peace and good Order at Home, are hardly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer'd or overcome. And, on the contrary, thoſe eaſily totter'd, which are diſturb'd with inteſtine Humours and Commotions.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="70" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE LXX.</hi> How to march an Army through a Foreign Countrey.</head>
               <p>THat the Treachery of Souldiers may be prevented, in a Foreign Country, care muſt be taken, that they march in ſeveral Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, unarm'd, and that the Kingdom or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth, who ſuffereth them to paſs, may have due Information, before they enter his Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritories; that Quarters may be provided, and what every one muſt pay be preſcrib'd.
<list>
                     <item>2. That the ſecond Body march the ſame way that the firſt marched; and that, if they be in great Bodies, they march not every Day.</item>
                     <item>(3.) That
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:65868:67"/>any Damage, done by the Souldiers, be made good.</item>
                     <item>4. That the Army do not approach any prohibited place, within a Mile.</item>
                     <item>5. That they do not quarter in Towns, or Cities, that are Walled or entrench'd.</item>
                     <item>6. That Commiſſaries and Proveditors go along with the Army, and ſet a rational price on all Proviſions, and curb the Inſolencies of the Souldiers.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="71" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE LXXI.</hi> How a Prince ſhould behave himſelf with a Contentions Neighbour more powerful than himſelf.</head>
               <p>IT is very ſafe for a Prince, who is in danger of War with a Prince more potent than himſelf, to yield up what formerly he hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered, to him whoſe former Right it was, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs he be able to maintain all Quarrels, by force. Neither will it be inconvenient, in time of great danger, to buy a Peace with Money, or the loſs of ſome Cities; for, beſides that all the reſt are ſecured, the ſhunning of a Bloody War, and the Enjoyment of a Happy Peace, make up all the loſs. But it is more Honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for a Prince, if he be able, to beat off an
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:65868:68"/>emulous Neighbour, turn'd to an open Enemy, in open Battle, by force of his own Arms, and the Aſſiſtance of his Allies; rather than that an Ambitious, Unſatisfied, Perfidious Prince, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Maſter of his Dominions. And, that the Enemy may do as little Miſchief as poſſible, it is neceſſary to hoard up the Proviſions in Stores and Granaries. But, if the Event anſwer not Expectation, it is neceſſary, that giving over the Care of Villages, and ſmall Towns; the whole power and ſtrength of the Country be brought to ſome Two or Three ſtrong fortified Places, till the Controverſie be compoſed. For, under ſuch Circumſtances, there will not be ſo much need of an Army, as of Garriſons, to preſerve what remaineth of Proviſions and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venues from the Hand of a Powerful and Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous Enemy.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="71" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE LXXI.</hi> How weaker Perſons may prolong Time in difficult Matters.</head>
               <p>THE prolonging of Time is, commonly, reputed a peculiar knack of the weaker ſort, for the more powerful uſe their craft, in
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:65868:68"/>wicked ambitious Deſigns, born out with a bold Confidence; and ſo it is folly for the meaner ſort to reſiſt them. And in ſuch deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Caſes, length of time bringeth ſome means of help along with it, eſpecially when the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my drives headlong and too furiouſly, with imprudence. Then, it is a point of Wiſdom, in one that is ſtill and quiet, to diſcover ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's Folly and Weakneſs; and from thence, find ſome opportunity to help himſelf. Thus, oft-times, great Intentions and Preparations of War, which at firſt were furious, through ſome Delayings, have come to nothing. But with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, this diſtinction is to be obſerved, That we muſt gain time, in thoſe things only, which can be better manag'd by Procraſtination. But in other things, where the dangers will ſtill recur, tho one delay and avoid them never ſo often, it is better to go through ſtitch and hazard at firſt, rather than at laſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="72" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE LXXII.</hi> How to deny a thing without Offence.</head>
               <p>IT is a hard matter for one to deny an earneſt Suit without Offence; but there are ſeveral courſes to be taken in this caſe: As firſt, To
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:65868:69"/>refer the granting or denying of ſuch and ſuch a thing, to the Arbitration of others. Thus <hi>Agamemnon</hi> ſerved <hi>Ajax</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>liſſes,</hi> when they ſtrove for <hi>Achilles</hi>'s Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour.<note place="margin">Ovids Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor. lib. 3.</note>
                  <list>
                     <item>(2.) Others have delay'd their Anſwer to ſome importunate Requeſt, that could not poſitively be deny'd, which may be cunningly put off by ſaying, <hi>I will conſider on't, and ſend you an anſwer that ſhall ſatisfie you, upon all Accounts.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>(3.) Others have deny'd what they had no mind to grant, by ſlighting and delaying the giving acceſs, to ſuch perſons as were to ask for great and dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult Matters.</item>
                     <item>(4.) Others have diſſwaded their Petitioners from their Suit, and have proffer'd them ſomewhat elſe, more conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient for both.</item>
                     <item>(5.) Others have, to cruſh the aſpiring Spirits of importunate Petitioners, raiſed up Competitors, who exceed their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervings, and to whom they muſt needs give the preheminence.</item>
                     <item>(6.) When a Petition is preſented, which poſitively cannot be denyed, one may feign himſelf willing to grant it, but in the mean time, propoſe ſuch hard and dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult Conditions, with ſuch intricat and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſom terms of Toil and Labour, that the Petitioner will think his Suit better denyed than granted.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="73" type="part">
               <pb n="121" facs="tcp:65868:69"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE LXXIII.</hi> How to compoſe Seditions by Interceſſors.</head>
               <p>IT is the drift of Factions, to ſtir up one part of the Government to claſh againſt another, affording cauſe for it, on both ſides: and when the Deſign is brought forth, in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of time, both parties, or one begins to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit Hoſtilities. <hi>Machiavel</hi> hath reduced the Remedies of Factions to three Heads, namely, The Reconciliation, the Death, or the Baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Heads of the Factions. But he hath not, with Subtility enough, diſtinguiſhed the matter, which muſt therefore, be thus explained: Firſt, When the divided Parties, on both ſides, are reconciled to the Homage of their Prince, promiſing that they will ſtand to his Determination; the Prince muſt not ſide with one Party more than the other, but im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partially weigh and cruſh their Feuds and Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rels with equal Reſpect; and ſhew himſelf a common Father to them both; and according to Equity and Juſtice, compoſe their Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies. Then, after all is in Peace and Quiet, the Prince ought to confirm their Unity by Marriages, or ſome other ſuch obliging Tyes,
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:65868:70"/>which naturally prompt to Affection and Love. But if the Controverſies cannot be compoſed (the Factions being ſo inveterate one againſt another, that they cannot acquieſce to the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Determination) the Prince, by his abſolute Authority, ſhould lay his Commands, to make no mention of their old Quarrels, or elſe ſend from Court, the Head of the Factions, upon ſome Embaſſie, or ſome ſuch pretence. But in this caſe, there is one caution to be obſerved, <hi>viz.</hi> That the Prince (as I have ſaid) be not more byaſs'd to one ſide than the other, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways a great many inconveniences will incur.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="74" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE LXXIV.</hi> How to Suppreſs Sedition by force.</head>
               <p>IF, of two Factious Parties, one ſhall dare, with down-right Saucineſs, or ſecret Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery, to control the King's Authority, let the Prince join himſelf to the other ſide, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come their Head; and by that means, when it cannot otherwiſe be, let him be avenged by force of their Treachery and Factions.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="75" type="part">
               <pb n="123" facs="tcp:65868:70"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE LXXV.</hi> How to Suppreſs Sedition by Force of Arms.</head>
               <p>WHEN two Factions bear not only ill-will to one another, but to the Prince likewiſe, then the Prince cannot ſuppreſs them both at once, neither ought he to ſide with one Party more than the other; nor to meddle or concern himſelf with them, in fomenting their Diviſions: nor to make himſelf a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moter of the ambition of others; nor become an inſtrument to procure his own and the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom's Miſery. For in ſuch a caſe, Money (which is the ſtrength and ſinews of publick Affairs) cannot be had but with great difficulty. And, when it fails, the Subjects Allegiance faileth with it: Namely, The Allegiance of ſuch Subjects as are byaſs'd with favour or fear of a Faction, to which they are related, either by Blood or Affinity, or obnoxious to their Favours on ſeveral Accounts. In this caſe the Prince himſelf muſt not take Arms, but, if he can by any means, pull Arms out of the hands of mad Men; ſo behaving himſelf, that whilſt one Faction is overcome, the other grow not too powerful and inſolent, without a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petitor. For the tumults of Faction gain moſt
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:65868:71"/>advantage in time of War, and are weakened in time of Peace. For in time of War, ſuch Subjects, as the guilt and conſciouſneſs of their Crimes, or deepneſs in Debt, ſtirs up to deſire and wiſh for change and alterations in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, do continually run to the Factious, never conſidering the juſtneſs of the Cauſe and Quarrel, ſo they can ſave themſelves from Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and Gibets, on the contrary in time of Peace, the Flames of animoſity are extinguiſh'd, the violence of Warlick Force ſtopt; the Storms ceaſe; the Waves become calm, and time will wear out the remembrance of all Rancor, Feuds, and Factions. For when they who are the Maintainers of and maintained by thoſe inteſtine Broils and Diſcords, are taken out of the way; a new Stock of People ariſes, who are Strangers to the former Tumults. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, another reaſon prefers Peace to War, which is, that in time of War the Treaſury is exhauſted, by laying out vaſt Sums of Money, which can never be filled again, till there be a well flouriſhing Peace. The Prince, therefore, muſt labour, by all means, to reconcile the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agreeing Parties; but if the obſtinacy of the Rebels ſhall reject Peace; what the Prince can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not openly do, he muſt attempt by ſome un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermining and cunning waies, leſt when one Faction is ſuppreſt, the other, that kept bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance with it, may too inſolently domineer.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="78" type="part">
               <pb n="125" facs="tcp:65868:71"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE LXXVIII.</hi> How to enter in Covenant.</head>
               <p>COvenants do diſcover a weak, unſtable and dubious State of Humane Affairs, And thoſe that are made with a People very remote, never procure help in due time. But the Friendſhip of two potent Neighbours is often treacherous and dangerous, to their weaker Neighbours; and to ſtand neuter hath oft proved beneficial, and as oft injurious. For as the Friendſhip of the weaker Neighbours affords little profit, ſo may one be weakned by being united to a more powerful Neighbour than himſelf. When both ſtand on equal ground, in time of danger, they may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted equals; but in time of Peace, the weaker maketh the leaſt Figure. The ſtronger muſt reap all the profit of the Victory; but both muſt equally partake of the danger and loſs; becauſe no new Line, according to the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the Lyons League, with weaker Beaſts (in the Fable) the Booty is alwaies yielded to the ſtrongeſt; it being the higheſt wiſh that that the weaker ſide can or dare to deſire, is to eſcape utter ruin. Moreover, the ſtronger oft
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:65868:72"/>provoketh the Enemy, and afterwards by a Peace, ſuddenly patch'd up, to ſet themſelves free of all danger, leave the weaker in the lurch. Politicians, furthermore, adviſe to keep and continue in Peace with thoſe, who have formerly been Enemies. But it is not an eaſie matter to enter in a League with them, or to put any confidence in thoſe who delight in Controverſies, and love to entertain Quarrels.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>How to keep up Favour and Authority at Court.</head>
                  <p>THERE are two ways, very oppoſite one to another, to keep Authority at Kings Courts; the firſt is to court Favour and Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the Prince, and thoſe who are neareſt to him in Blood, and have the chief ſway next him, to accompany them often; and to owe to their Good-will, the foundation of all ones Power and Preferment. The next is to rely on ones own Strength, and not on ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; and being conſcious of no ill Deſign, to defeat the Artifice of envious Competitors.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="78" type="part">
               <pb n="127" facs="tcp:65868:72"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE LXXVIII.</hi> How a Prince that is at Peace, ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>have, when his Neighbours are in War.</head>
               <p>PRINCES, who profeſs leaſt of Ill-will (either through fear, or becauſe whilſt others are diſputing for Intereſt by Arms, think it ſafer to wait for the event of the War) do privately help ſome daring Party with Money or their Advice. However, when the event falleth out according to their wiſh, they can be confident enough to declare openly for the Conqueror.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="79" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE LXXIX.</hi> How to confine great States-men.</head>
               <p>THESE are neceſſary Cautions, in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fining Seditious States-men. Firſt, To chooſe for them Priſons, which are not fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quented by many Viſiters, with Apartments every way ſtrong and fenc'd with Iron-Bars.
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:65868:73"/>
                  <list>
                     <item>(2.) It is very neceſſary to give them but little Liberty, and whilſt they are Priſoners, to ſuffer them to take the Air but ſeldom, and never to allow them to ride out or go a Hunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</item>
                     <item>(3.) To remove from them thoſe who have formerly been their Servants, and put Strangers in their room.</item>
                     <item>(4.) To ſearch all things that are carried into the Priſon; nay, their very Proviſions, Ieſt, together with other Things, Tools for Breaking the Priſon, Ropes, Crows, Pick axes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> be conveyed to them.</item>
                     <item>(5.) To change their Keepers often, leſt long acquaintance and Familiarity give occaſion of corrupting them by Bribes.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="80" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE LXXX.</hi> How to Disband Souldiers.</head>
               <p>IT is no ways ſafe to Disband a whole Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, in time of ſuſpected Peace, or in time of a ſhort Truce; and therefore prudent Princes, judging it better to looſe their Money than their Army, do not Disband all: But ſtill keep a ſufficient Force in Arms, to ſecure the publick Peace. But ſome who Disband their Army's, diſcharge only ſuch as conn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Live without their Pay; and ſo can be eaſily
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:65868:73"/>brought to take Arms again, upon occaſion: Whilſt they keep thoſe who might ſeem to be more unwilling to be Liſted again.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="84" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE LXXXIV.</hi> How Mineſters of State may avoid great Dangers.</head>
               <p>THey are a Wicked ſort of People, who, without any neceſſity of their Duty, but through meer Malice, do ſtir up or cheriſh animoſities betwixt Princes. However, they ſtand on ſlippery Ground, and are ready to Totter, who ſerve an Antient Prince, or him who is the next Heir: For the Old Prince will take it Ill, that the Riſing Son ſhould only be regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by his Subjects; and the Young Heir com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly takes it as a contempt of himſelf, to be look'd upon as a Subject, and to be courted with no Homage or Reſpect. But, if ſuch be the danger and offence of neglected Duty, it is an evident conſequence, that thoſe Miniſters do far more undergo Danger, who diſcharge Offices, and pay their Duty both to Father and Son; but it is the ſafeſt courſe of ſteering a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midſt ſuch Rocks, for one to get the name of an honeſt Man, and apply himſelf to all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns,
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:65868:74"/>tending to Peace and Reconciliation; to go about the ſervice of his Maſter carefully, and to Court with obliging Duty and Humour, the apparent Heir; to Write no Letters but ſuch as are ſeen of the Prince. Furthermore, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>have ſo, as to approve Allegience to his Prince, Reſpect to the Succeſſor, and to both, a peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Affection.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="85" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE LXXXV.</hi> How to Aſpire to Promotion.</head>
               <p>IT is no hard matter for them whoſe Noble Pedigree, their good Character, and great Employment do elevate, to come to be known by their Prince; and to lay out ways for a higher Preferment. But they who have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to commend them but their own parts and qualifications, and can ſhew no Coat of Arms of their Anceſtors, cannot obtain the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of their <hi>Prince,</hi> but by chance, or the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commendation of ſome Noble Peer: And yet it commonly falls out, that the Promotion of the latter is more ſtable than that of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, which appears, either becauſe the former thinking that all is due upon the ſcore of their Antient Nobility, never court the favour of
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:65868:74"/>any Patron; whilſt the latter do, with all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry, ſtrive to obtain the favour of ſome great Perſon, which is like to continue their preferment: Or becauſe <hi>Princes,</hi> in imitation of Nature, love <hi>generare &amp; corrumpere,</hi> to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote the Inferiour, and caſt down the Lofty. Therefore, to ward oft pinching neceſſity and poverty of one's Family, and to catch ſome high preferment, one muſt needs ſcrew his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt among ſome ſtrong Faction, and procure for himſelf the favour of ſome great Patron, with all the duty, humble reſpects, and artifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial ſhews imaginable: And the getting into the favour of the Female Sex hath often been very profitable in affairs of this Nature.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="86" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE LXXXVI.</hi> How to delay an Inevitable War.</head>
               <p>IF a Prince meet with ſuch intollerable pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocations, that he muſt of neceſſity under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go the hazard of a dangerous War, and would delay it, till affairs be put in a Poſture; it is neceſſary that he ſeem condeſcending to all the Articles and Overtures which his Enemy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth; rather than to undergo the danger of
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:65868:75"/>to ſend counterfeit Plenipotentiary Miniſters of State, who on the firſt Addreſs may ſeem ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry complying, but referring ſome unexpected propoſals of great weight to his Maſters Deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination. Likewiſe, if by his advice, and at his earneſt requeſt, there be ſent an Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſador to his Maſter, it will be Policy to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangle him in ſuch a Labyrinth of Affairs, out of which he cannot extricat himſelf, without the help and advice of both Princes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="87" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE LXXXVII.</hi> How to Govern New Provinces.</head>
               <p>THE Governour of a New Province, muſt not careſs himſelf in Pleaſures, but ought to underſtand the nature of Affairs, and learn a true account thereof, from thoſe who can inform him: And what time others do ſpend in Oſtentation, he is to accomodate to his Buſineſs.
<list>
                     <item>(2.) He muſt take care that vigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Beginnings end not in a ſupine Negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence.</item>
                     <item>(3.) That he be not given to change, by obtruding new Cuſtoms on the Province.</item>
                     <item>(4.) He muſt not find fault with, nor reſcind what hath been done by his Anceſtours; nay he muſt behold as in a Looking-glaſs, all their
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:65868:75"/>Vertues and Vices.</item>
                     <item>(5.) Above all things, he muſt govern his own Family well.</item>
                     <item>(6.) He muſt give eaſie Acceſs, and lay out his Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for every occaſion, and perform Affairs in due time.</item>
                     <item>(7.) He muſt ſhake off Sullen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Pride.</item>
                     <item>(8.) He muſt behave him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſo, that his eaſie temper do not diminiſh his Authority, nor his Severity the Love and Reſpect of the Subjects.</item>
                     <item>(9.) Let him not reſolve upon any thing in Paſſion.</item>
                     <item>(10.) Let him be familiar but with few.</item>
                     <item>(11.) Let every Office of Juſtice be adminiſtred with all care.</item>
                     <item>(12.) Let him have greater Reſpect for the publick Peace, than to rigid Juſtice.</item>
                     <item>(13.) Let him not be byaſſed by Favour or Hatred, in giving Judgment.</item>
                     <item>(14.) He muſt, if poſſible, avoid all Controverſies, with the People of the Province: or, if he hath to do with private Quarrels, he had better yield the Cauſe, and paſs from his own Intereſt.</item>
                     <item>(15.) He muſt avoid Controverſies with the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours of Neighbouring Provinces.</item>
                     <item>(16.) Let him be very cautious that the breach of Peace, with a neighbouring Prince, be not imputed to him.</item>
                     <item>(17.) He muſt make ſmal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler Affairs, to repreſent the Draught and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of his greater.</item>
                     <item>(18.) He muſt vindicate the Rights of all Officers and Souldiers, that ſerve under him.</item>
                     <item>(19.) In Dangerous Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, he ought ſo to behave himſelf, that all
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:65868:76"/>may acknowledge that it is not by his, but the Princes Authority, that all Affairs are managed.</item>
                     <item>(20.) He ought not to diſturb the Prince with triffling matters, nor do any thing of greater weight without his Advice.</item>
                     <item>(21.) He muſt keep up his Friendſhip at Court, by Gifts and Preſents.</item>
                     <item>(22.) He ſhould ſhew himſelf fit for his Buſineſs, but not as he were above it. For as Princes in chuſing of their Miniſters, hate Vice, ſo do they not much like of ambitious and aſpiring Vertues.</item>
                     <item>(23.) He muſt never brag too much of his own Feats, but attribute them to his Prince as Author, or to his good Fortune.</item>
                  </list> Thus, by Valour in his Obedience, and by Modeſty in telling of his Actions, he ſhall be beyond Envy, and ſhall not miſs of Honour.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="88" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE LXXXVIII.</hi> How to eſtabliſh and ſettle new Conqueſts.</head>
               <p>IN ſettling new Conqueſts, the chief point of Prudence, conſiſteth in perſuading the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, that they are in a better caſe under their new Prince, than under the former; according to <hi>Tacitus; Clementiam nova imperiainchoantibus, uti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem eſſe, ut prioribus tributis quaedam diminuantur;
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:65868:76"/>quo mitius Imperium videatur.</hi> Clemency is of great uſe to them that adventure upon new Conqueſts, and that ſome of the former Taxes be remitted, to the end that the Government may ſeem more eaſie.
<list>
                     <item>(2) People are taken with no bait ſo much as plenty of Proviſion, care for the publick Peace, adminiſtration of impartial Juſtice.</item>
                     <item>(3) New Conquerors may, very effectually, gain the good will of their Subjects, by Liberality and Munificence, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Merit, Moderation and Prudence; and then, after, they may promote to Honours and Dignities, ſuch as ſtick cloſeſt to their Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt.</item>
                     <item>(4.) Good uſe may likewiſe be made of Schools, and the Education of Youth, for People learn Obedience and Allegiance to their Prince, from none ſo much as from School-Maſters and Clergy-Men.</item>
                     <item>(5.) It is very con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient, to joyn in Marriage the Ancient and upſtart Citizens; for it is an excellent Bond of Friendſhip and Society, ſo as thoſe, who for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly were at diſtance, may make up one Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and agree in the ſame Manners.</item>
                     <item>(6.) It is Tyrannical to Debauch, with looſe Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, diſſolute Manners, or Luxury, the Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of the People, which yet is dreaded and ſuſpected by a faint-hearted Prince.</item>
                     <item>(7.) The preſence of the Prince, which procures Veneration from the Subjects, prevents, or over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throws Plots and Conſpiracies, and conduceth
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:65868:77"/>very much to eſtabliſh the Government.</item>
                     <item>(8.) Great Expences of the Court, upon their ſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Buildings, Fair, and great Pomp doth maintain and enrich a great many of the poorer ſort of People, and conſequently gaineth the Affection of the Subjects.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="89" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE LXXXIX.</hi> How to Compoſe the Differences of the Nobility.</head>
               <p>THE Differences of the Nobility at Court, of Magiſtrates, or Officers, which threaten no harm or inconveniency to the publick good, muſt not be decided, ſo as that the Prince ſhould condemn one ſide, and be for the other; but rather provide for the Honour of both Parties.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="90" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE XC.</hi> How one muſt behave that feareth a Repulſe.</head>
               <p>THey who fear a Repulſe, uſe to deal by Emiſſaries and Meſſengers, who pretend
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:65868:77"/>to have no Charge or Commiſſion; but act as they did all freely of their own Head.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="91" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE XCI.</hi> What Policy muſt be uſed by a General.</head>
               <p>IT is a point of great Policy in a General, to make good uſe of the ſuddain fear of his Enemy, and increaſe it by their own Courage and Severity; and afterwards, by being favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, to gain the Reputation of Clemency.
<list>
                     <item>2. To March againſt an Enemy, with an Army that ſeemeth not ſerious or vindictive, leſt they loſe all hope of Pardon and Peace.</item>
                     <item>3. It is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient to uſe divers Arts, in ſhewing Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency to thoſe that ſubmit themſelves, to his Mercy.</item>
                     <item>4. To purſue them that are in flight, with all Expedition, but to be gentle to all but the ſtubborn.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="92" type="part">
               <pb n="138" facs="tcp:65868:78"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE XCII.</hi> How to cruſh Reproachful Speeches.</head>
               <p>IT is a Secret belonging to Arbitrary Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to give full Liberty to the Malice and Envy of the baſer ſort, and to vent themſelves in Calumnies and falſe Reports; ſo, that when they have ſpoke very Ill of Brave and Worthy Men, at length, finding their own Reputation and Fortune to lie at Stake; they by their Fooliſh Revenge, may be brought to forbear.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="93" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE XCIII.</hi> How to obtain leave to depart from Court.</head>
               <p>HE that is with a Maſter, from whom he hath a mind to depart, and yet to ask leave of departing is dangerous, (as commonly it is with Tyrannical Maſters) muſt make heavy Complaints; and then beg leave, not as if you were to go away at preſent, but a great while after; and ſo he will not take it ſo very ill; and yet, in the mean time, others gaping for his
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:65868:78"/>Place, will take Care that he may have Liberty to go at Pleaſure, and will uſe all endeavours to gain ground upon his Maſter, to grant him his Deſire. During which time, he muſt act all things raſhly, diſorderly, and in a Tumult; until, that for asking his leave, and the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>management of his Affairs, he ſhall utterly hate him. Then, when he is aſſured of this, he may be of him that he would keep him ſtill, and with dejected Sighs, and Groans, and ſhews of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, make uſe of Perſons, for whom the Prince hath no great liking, to intercede for him; and thus the Prince will think he hath ſufficiently puniſh'd him, by granting him leave to depart with ſo much Reluctancy and Unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingneſs: Whilſt he, in the mean time, ſhall enjoy his Deſire, without any loſs or danger: But he muſt beware that he do not preſently brag, or boaſt of his Wit or Contrivance; other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways he may thereby, incur great danger: Therefore ſhould continue ſeeming ſorrowful, as if he were griev'd for his Misfortune.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="94" type="part">
               <pb n="140" facs="tcp:65868:79"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE XCIV.</hi> How to avoid Envy.</head>
               <p>IT is a very ſafe Courſe, for all who would live peaceably, with conſtancy in good Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to reſiſt and trample under Foot all Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumnies (which are the chief Weapons that Envy uſeth) and by Prudent Councels, Fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and Diligence, not only to enjoy, but like-ways to deſerve the Favour both of Prince and People. And, laſt of all, to oblige Competi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors with all Civilities, Courteſies, and kind Offices; and, as far as poſſible, to avoid all ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of vain Glory, Pride, and Oſtentation; and to refrain, or at leaſt not to brag of, any great Retinue, or Train of Attendants; or to Head, as it were, an Army of Servants; to have a neat Dwelling-Houſe and Furniture, rather than that which is coſtly. Moreover it will leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen Envy, when it appeareth that one doth not Court Dignities ſo much as they Court him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="95" type="part">
               <pb n="141" facs="tcp:65868:79"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE XCV.</hi> How to ſhare Dominions among Brothers.</head>
               <p>MOST Nations do condeſcend that, for avoiding thoſe Inconveniencies which ariſe from ſharing Eſtates; the chief Power, Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and Government be given only to the El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt Child; all the reſt of the Children being deprived of all Inheritance, but what ſerveth for their Subſiſtance: which Cuſtom, (tho it croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes the Law of Nature, by which, the Condition and Right of Brothers ſtandeth in equal terms, and ballance) is defended by the publick Benefit, whereof all Care muſt be taken: altho, in that Caſe alſo the rigour thereof is ſo far di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſhed, that the ſame Cuſtom doth provide that the other Children of both Sexes, be not abdicated like Baſtards, but be ſupplied by the Elder Brother, with Dignities, Wealth, and other Neceſſaries, becoming the Royal Progeny. But in ſharing of Dominions, theſe Cautions are to be obſerved.
<list>
                     <item>1. That whatever <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors</hi> are alotted to the Children of Princes, they return to the Prince without any Encumbrance, if the Brothers ſhall die without Male-Iſſue (un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs the Law of the Country provide otherways.)
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:65868:80"/>But the Daughters of Princes ſhould only have ſuch Portions, as that the Prerogatives of the Crown be not impaired, but the Dominions kept intire, and in the ſame Caſe as they uſed to be lineally transferr'd.</item>
                     <item>(2.) It is neceſſary that what ever lands, or Revenues, are alotted to bring up the young Brothers, be received immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately at the Hands of the Prince: So that, for fear of loſing them, the Brothers may be obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to owe true Allegiance, who otherways, through the default of depraved Nature, or wicked Guardians, may be eaſily perſuaded to turn aſide.</item>
                     <item>(3.) Care muſt be taken that the Charge of the Army be never committed to the Royal Brothers, for nothing is more dangerous than to give the command of the Sword, at home and abroad, to one of the Royal Family; ſeeing, many times, ſuch as are come of a low Pedigree, and baſer ſort, when they arrive at high preferment, have aimed at great Things, and been much dreaded.</item>
                     <item>(4.) Wiſe Men do adviſe, that if neceſſity force the Sword to be given to one of the Royal Family, a Conjunct or Part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſhould be added to him, who may obſerve and curb his Ambitious and Aſpiring Hopes.</item>
                     <item>(5.) It is convenient to recommend to the Royal Brothers, ſuch Servants as are Prudent and Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to the Prince, and to change them now and then, and to place new ones in their ſtead, ſo as to break their Meaſures, which may be dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:65868:80"/>to the Common-wealth, through a long continued Courſe of good Liking and Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liarity.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="96" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE XCVI.</hi> How to obſerve the due Time of making Truce.</head>
               <p>IT is thought prudent, upon three Accounts, to make a Truce.
<list>
                     <item>(1.) When the Truce lays open a way for Peace.</item>
                     <item>(2.) When a Prince find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth himſelf deſtitute of Proviſions neceſſary to continue the War. For a Treaſury exhauſted, and an Army wearied with Fatigues and Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents of War, cannot be recruited but by a Truce, which makes way for Peace. And as it is the Intereſt of the ſtrongeſt Party to purſue ſtrongly their firſt Deſigns, and to proſecute the Courſe of Victory; ſo it concerns the weaker ſide, by obtaining time, to gain ground upon the Enemy and to get opportunity to renew their Courage; and, commonly, in this Caſe, a Truce is profitable to one, and hurtful to the other.</item>
                     <item>(3.) Care muſt be taken that when Hoſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities ceaſe for a while, and the Care, Vigilancy, and Induſtry of the Enemy is much bent for War, to diſtract them with inteſtine Diſcords, Broils, and Commotions.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <pb n="142" facs="tcp:65868:81"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="143" facs="tcp:65868:81"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </div>
            <div n="97" type="part">
               <pb n="144" facs="tcp:65868:82"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE XCVII.</hi> How to change Commanders of an Army.</head>
               <p>IT hath been obſerved by all Politicians, even thoſe of the beſt Rank, that hardly any bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs was ever well managed, by the Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of an Army, bearing equal Sway and Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er: Yet Cardinal <hi>Richelieu,</hi> according to his Prudence, found out a Remedy for this Evil: When he had ſet three Commanders over the Army in <hi>Italy</hi> (as miſtruſting the Valour of one ſingle Perſon to be ſufficient for an Office of ſo great importance) on thoſe Terms; according to the Courſe of Weeks; he appointed one to lead the <hi>Van,</hi> another the <hi>Main Body,</hi> and the third the <hi>Reer,</hi> and that he who led the <hi>Main-Body</hi> ſhould for that Week have the higheſt Command.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="98" type="part">
               <pb n="145" facs="tcp:65868:82"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE XCVIII.</hi> How to draw up an Army.</head>
               <p>AN Army muſt be drawn up ſo, as that it cannot be ſurrounded, either whole, or part, by the Enemy.
<list>
                     <item>2. Room muſt be left for the Horſe, to encounter the Enemy, when they are in Battle.</item>
                     <item>3. The main Strength of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my muſt oppoſe the main Strength of the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my; but eſpecially thoſe Souldiers who have been accuſtomed to Fight with ſuch an Enemy.</item>
                     <item>4. The hindermoſt or Reer Ranks muſt not march forwards until the formoſt, in the ſame Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny or Troop, march before them.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="99" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE XCIX.</hi> How Ambaſſadors and Mediators may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure Peace.</head>
               <p>AMongſt a great many Precepts which Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal <hi>Franciſcus Barbariny,</hi> in his <hi>Secret</hi> Commands brought along with him from <hi>Rome,</hi> theſe are the chief.
<list>
                     <item>1. A Miniſter of State ſhould
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:65868:83"/>not be biaſs'd with Affection to either ſide, but impartial to both; otherways, he ſhall loſe all the Confidence and Authority they may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe in him.</item>
                     <item>2. That he ſhall not give leave to his Domeſtick Servants or Acquaintance to Argue, far leſs, ſend Letters about publick Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, either amongſt one another, or the Servants of other Ambaſſadours.</item>
                     <item>3. He muſt not propoſe any Terms or Conditions of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation, but what Arguments are offered of one ſide, he ſhould faithfully Communicate to the other; adding only ſo many of his own Arguments, as may perſuade one ſide to embrace the other's Propoſals, omitting all thoſe which might embroil fortunate beginnings, or the good procedure of Affairs.</item>
                     <item>4. He muſt judge it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to his Quality and Dignity, to propoſe Peace or Conditions to no ſide more than the other; and ſo it will be the part of an Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trator, to invite them both, that he may, at the ſame time, give their Propoſals; or that both may ſend their Demands in Writing to the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrator.</item>
                     <item>5. He muſt not become Arbitrator to their Controverſies, when the Caſe cannot conſiſt with the Duty, or be decided by an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrator.</item>
                     <item>6. He muſt not take a Pledge or <hi>Depoſitum</hi> of a Letigious Matter.</item>
                     <item>7. He muſt not ſend his Expreſſes or Cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>riers to Kings or Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, who may extort an Aſſent or Diſſent from them with Reluctancy; but with thoſe Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:65868:83"/>which are ſent by Ambaſſadours, he may ſend his own Letter.</item>
                     <item>8. If he muſt needs write to them apart, let him uſe the Intereſt of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, who have Dealings in ſeveral Foreign Places.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="100" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE C.</hi> How to Diſſemble the Deſire of Peace.</head>
               <p>PEace and Concord are often boaſted of, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Specious, and yet vain and empty pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences; and that for ſeveral Reaſons.
<list>
                     <item>(1.) That the Enemy being deceived with the hope of Peace, and the care of providing neceſſary Proviſions of War ſlighted, may at length be ſurprized and catch'd unawares.</item>
                     <item>(2.) That, when we our ſelves are unprovided, we may gain time to raiſe an Army.</item>
                     <item>(3.) We pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to negotiate a Peace with an Enemy, and to have matters of great Concern with him, to the intent we may obtain of our Allies, what we deſire through fear, leſt we ſhould break off from them.</item>
                     <item>(4.) Sometimes we negotiate a Peace with one of our Enemies Allies, not for any hope of ſucceeding, but only to raiſe Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpition and Animoſities among themſelves.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="101" type="part">
               <pb n="148" facs="tcp:65868:84"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE CI.</hi> The Cauſes of Animoſities and Inſurrections.</head>
               <p>THE main and moſt endearing Cauſe of Aſſociations amongſt the People, is a pretence of Reſpect to the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, repreſented with great Zeal, and preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed home to be much regarded.
<list>
                     <item>2. An Indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation ariſing from Calumnies, or ſuppoſed ſo to be, and a deſire of Revenge thereupon, is a Means Incendiaries much uſe.</item>
                     <item>3. They con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute very much to an Inſurrection againſt the Prince and Magiſtrates, who have but ſmall For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes, and are in ſorry Circumſtances, in time of Peace; and therefore they ſtrive to raiſe Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mults, becauſe they may go more ſcot-free, when things are in Confuſion, and be ſafer in Troubleſome Times.</item>
                     <item>4. Fear and Danger are not the leaſt Cauſe of Aſſociations; for obnoxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Men dread the Laws, and the Puniſhments due to their Crimes; as alſo, good Men fear In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries and the Violence of Tyranny, and ſo both Deſire to prevent and ward off their impending danger, by their Aſſociations.</item>
                     <item>5. Sometimes a vain glorious Name or Renown, may ſtir up ſome to an Aſſociation.</item>
                     <item>6. Above all, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>he Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:65868:84"/>Ingratitude, in not rewarding thoſe who have deſerved well of him, raiſeth Heart-burnings and Animoſities among all ſorts of Subjects.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="102" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>INTRIGUE CII.</hi> What Cautions are to be uſed in propoſing difficult Matters.</head>
               <p>THE Deceitful Propoſals of Incredible things, are to be avoided; and the Artifices of Impoſtors, wherewith they commonly cheat Princes of their Wealth, ought to be examined before they be believed; for great Pretenders, the more eaſily to attain their ends, perſuade Princes to be at ſome ſmall coſt, to acquire great gains; as to level Mountains, turn the Courſes of Rivers, to look out for Treaſures, and Mines of Gold, to invent new Engines, to Tranſubſtantiate Mettals, to find out the Philoſopher's Stone, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> whereby, with their Deceitful Confidence, they ſeem to provoke and force Nature her ſelf: Yet, as we muſt not altogether believe them, ſo muſt we not abſolutely ſlight and reject them; but the Author's Sincerity muſt be obſerved, and Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors ſent, to find out whether he offereth any
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:65868:85"/>feaſible Propoſal, which muſt be conſulted up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and tried by competent Judges; ſo that nothing may be undertaken raſhly; for here the <hi>Italian</hi> Proverb, and Rule taketh place, <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gran parti parti-ti;</hi> that is to ſay, <hi>Beware of them who promiſe too much gain.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:65868:85"/>
            <head>Books Printed for, and Sold by, <hi>Thomas Howkins,</hi> in <hi>George-Yard,</hi> in <hi>Lom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bard-Street.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>DR. <hi>Wedenfield</hi>'s Chymiſtry, concerning the Secrets of the Adepts, or the Uſe of <hi>Lul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi>'s Spirit of Wine, in <hi>Quarto.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Everard</hi>'s Works, in large <hi>Octavo.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mandy</hi>'s Marrow of Meaſuring, illuſtrated with Copper-Plates, in <hi>Octavo.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Angliae Motropolis:</hi> or, the preſent State of <hi>London,</hi> by <hi>Tho. Delaune,</hi> Gen. Print. <hi>An.</hi> 1690.</item>
               <item>The Baniſh'd Duke, or the Tragedy of <hi>Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunatus.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Midnight Thoughts; the Third Edition, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged, in <hi>Octavo.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Holwel</hi>'s Trigonometry, fitted to the meaneſt capacity, in <hi>Octavo.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mythologia Ethica:</hi> Or, Three Centuries of <hi>Eſopian</hi> Fables, by <hi>Philip Ayres,</hi>
                  <abbr>Eſq</abbr> in large <hi>Octavo.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Narrow Path of Divine Truth deſcrib'd, from Living, Practice and Experience, of its Three great Steps, <hi>viz. Purgation, Illumination,</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion,</hi> By <hi>F. M. Vun Helmont.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:65868:86"/>The Treaſury of <hi>Druggs</hi> Unlock'd, or a f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> and true Deſcription of all ſorts of <hi>Druggs,</hi> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Chymical Preparations, ſold by <hi>Druggiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> whereby one may know the place of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Growth, and how to diſtinguiſh the good fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the bad.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Culpepper</hi>'s Phyſical Receipts, in <hi>Octa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> Price 6 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Art of ſhort and ſwift Writing, wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> out any Characters, or trouble to the Memo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> in <hi>Octavo.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Experienc'd Inſtructor; a Copy-bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Printed in Red, for the eaſe of the Lear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Price 6 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Gloria Britannica:</hi> or the Boaſt of the <hi>Br<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> Seas, containing a true and full Account of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Royal Navy of <hi>England;</hi> ſhewing where <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Ship was Built, by whom, and when; its leng<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> bredth, depth, draught of Water; Tuns, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> number of Men and Guns, both in Peace <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> War, at home and abroad; together, with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Man's Pay, from a Captain to a Cabbin-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> truly caſt up, for a Day, a Week, a Month, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> a Kalendar Year, or 13 Months and a Day; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> fully Collected and Digeſted, by a true Love Seamen, and one of long Experience in the P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices of the Navy and Admiralty. Price 1 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
               <item>With Paper and Paper Books, Blank-Bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> and Releaſes of all ſorts, with the beſt Ink <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Records.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
